<TCase ID="133 ITR (Trib) 0754" Shtitle="Ashita Garg v. JAO (Chand)" Appendix="N">
	<CaseId>
		<Pagenum>
			<ShCourtName>(Chandigarh)</ShCourtName>
		</Pagenum>
	</CaseId>
	<court>
		<CourtName>Income-tax Appellate Tribunal</CourtName>
		<Bench Special="n">
			Chandigarh “SMC” Bench
		</Bench>
	</court>
	<CauseTitleGroup>
		<CauseTitle>
			<ApellantGroup>
				<Apellant Type="Apellant">
					Ashita Garg<Footnote>1</Footnote>
				</Apellant>
			</ApellantGroup>
			<RespondentGroup>
				<Respondent>Jurisdictional Assessing Officer</Respondent>
			</RespondentGroup>
		</CauseTitle>
	</CauseTitleGroup>
	<JudGroup>
		<TJudge Position1="Accountant Member" Position2="None">
			Vikram
			Singh Yadav
		</TJudge>
	</JudGroup>
	<Date Month="August" Date="18" Year="2025"/>
	<SRGroup>
		<Sr>
			<ActAbbr>ITA 1961,</ActAbbr>
			<SecNum> ss 144B</SecNum>
			<SecNum>148</SecNum>
			<SecNum>148A</SecNum>
			<SecNum>151A</SecNum>
		</Sr>
	</SRGroup>
	<AssYearGroup>
		<AssYear>2019-20</AssYear>
	</AssYearGroup>
	<HFGroup>
		<Hf Favourof="Assessee"/>
	</HFGroup>
	<CWGroup>
		<CW>Income-tax</CW>
		<CW>Reassessment</CW>
		<CW>Notice</CW>
		<CW>Jurisdiction</CW>
		<CW>Notification laying down proceedings to be undertaken by faceless assessment unit</CW>
		<CW>
			Show-cause notice issued by jurisdictional Assessing Officer
			instead of faceless assessment unit
		</CW>
		<CW>
			Held,<page no="755"></page>breach of binding
			notification
		</CW>
		<CW>
			Notice under section <SecRef ID="ITA-1961-148">148</SecRef> to
			be issued by faceless assessment unit
		</CW>
		<CW>
			Reassessment invalid
			and quashed
		</CW>
		<CW>
			<ActName>Income-tax Act, 1961</ActName>, ss.
			<SecRef ID="ITA-1961-144B">144B</SecRef>,
			<SecRef ID="ITA-1961-148">148</SecRef>, <SecRef ID="ITA-1961-148A">148A</SecRef>,
			<SecRef ID="ITA-1961-151A">151A</SecRef>
		</CW>
		<CW>
			Central Board
			of Direct Taxes Notification No. 18 of 2022/F. No. 370142/16/2022-TPL
			(Part 1), dated 29-3-2022<Footnote>2</Footnote>.
		</CW>
	</CWGroup>
	<?Fm Condstart FM8_SYSTEM_HIDEELEMENT?>
	<CSGroup hidden="y">
		<CS>Income-tax</CS>
		<CS>Reassessment</CS>
		<CS>Notice</CS>
		<CS>Jurisdiction</CS>
	</CSGroup>
	<?Fm Condend FM8_SYSTEM_HIDEELEMENT?>
	<HeadNote>
		<Para>
			For the assessment year 2019-20, a show-cause notice
			was issued under section <SecRef ID="ITA-1961-148A-b">148A(b)</SecRef> of
			the <ActName>Income-tax Act, 1961</ActName> by the jurisdictional
			Assessing Officer on March 2, 2023 calling upon the assessee to
			show cause why notice under section <SecRef ID="ITA-1961-148">148</SecRef> should
			not be issued on the basis of information that -income chargeable
			to tax had escaped assessment. After the assessee’s submission,
			order under section <SecRef ID="ITA-1961-148A-d">148A(d)</SecRef> was
			passed on March 30, 2023 and on the same date, notice under section
			<SecRef ID="ITA-1961-148">148</SecRef> was issued by the jurisdictional
			Assessing Officer. The Commissioner (Appeals) affirmed the reassessment.
			On appeal to the -Tribunal raising an additional ground that the
			reassessment proceedings were invalid having been undertaken by
			the jurisdictional Assessing Officer and not by the faceless assessment
			unit, as required by notification dated March 29, 20221 :
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<EmphasisR>Held</EmphasisR>, allowing the appeal, that the
			notice under section <SecRef ID="ITA-1961-148">148</SecRef> was
			issued by the jurisdictional Assessing Officer and not by the faceless
			assessment unit, almost a year after the issuance of the notification
			by the Ministry of Finance, Government of India on March 29, 2022
			requiring issuance of notice and conduct of assessment proceedings
			by the faceless assessment unit. There was thus a clear breach of
			the binding notification issued under section
			<SecRef ID="ITA-1961-144B">144B</SecRef> of the Act requiring
			issuance of notices and conduct of proceedings through the faceless
			assessment unit. Thus, the notice issued was without jurisdiction and
			bad in law. <EmphasisR>(para 10)</EmphasisR>
		</Para>
		<JDNotice>
			<JDN>
				<Title>Dy. CIT v. Aman Batra</Title> <Citothers>
					2025
					SCC OnLine ITAT 6348
				</Citothers>, <Title>
					Bagga Singh v. Dy. CIT (International
					Taxation)
				</Title> <Citothers>2025 SCC OnLine ITAT 6284</Citothers>,
				<Title>Jatinder Singh Bhangu v. Union of India</Title>
				<Citation Citation="466 ITR 474" year="2024" Court="P&amp;H" fbsb="0"/> ; <Citothers>
					2024 SCC OnLine P&amp;H
					9337
				</Citothers> and <Title>Jasjit Singh v. Union of India</Title>
				<Citation Citation="467 ITR 52" year="2024" Court="P&amp;H" fbsb="0"/> ;
				<Citothers>2024 SCC OnLine P&amp;H 9677</Citothers> <JDType>followed</JDType>.
			</JDN>
		</JDNotice>
		<Para>
			<Italics>Chronological list of cases cited 	on page(s)</Italics>
		</Para>
		<Referred>
			<CRT>
				<Citothers>2025 SCC OnLine ITAT 6348</Citothers>,
				<Title>CIT (Dy.) v. Aman Batra</Title> 	757f, 759g
			</CRT>
			<CRT>
				<Citothers>2025 SCC OnLine ITAT 6284</Citothers>, <Title>
					Bagga
					Singh v. Dy. CIT
					(International Taxation)
				</Title> 		759c, g
			</CRT>
			<CRT>
				<Citation Citation="467 ITR 52" year="2024" Court="P&amp;H" fbsb="0"/> ;
				<Citothers>2024 SCC OnLine P&amp;H 9677</Citothers>, <Title>
					Jasjit
					Singh
					v. Union of India
				</Title> 		758e-f
			</CRT>
			<page no="756"></page>
			<CRT>
				<Citation Citation="466 ITR 474" year="2024" Court="P&amp;H" fbsb="0"/> ; <Citothers>
					2024 SCC OnLine P&amp;H
					9337
				</Citothers>, <Title>
					Jatinder
					Singh Bhangu v. Union of India
				</Title> 		756f, 758d-e, f
			</CRT>
			<CRT>
				<Citation Citation="229 ITR 383" year="1998" Court="SC" fbsb="0"/> ;
				<Citation Citation="132 STC 566" year="2003" Court="SC" fbsb="0"/> ;
				<Citothers>
					(1997) 7
					SCC 489
				</Citothers> ; <Citothers>1996 SCC OnLine SC 173</Citothers>,
				<Title>
					National Thermal Power
					Co. Ltd. v. CIT
				</Title> 		756g, 757a
			</CRT>
		</Referred>
		<TaxCaseNo>
			<Ref>I. T. A. No.</Ref>
			<Caseno>
				<Number>539</Number>/Chand/
				<year>2025</year> (assessment year <AssYear>2019-20</AssYear>).
			</Caseno>
		</TaxCaseNo>
		<CounselGroup>
			<forApellant>
				<CounselName>Ms. Pallavi</CounselName> and
				<CounselName>Sudhir Sehgal</CounselName>, Advocates, for the assessee.
			</forApellant>
			<forRespondent>
				<CounselName>Vivek Vardhan</CounselName>, Additional
				Commissioner of Income-tax, Senior -Departmental representative,
				for the Department.
			</forRespondent>
		</CounselGroup>
	</HeadNote>
	<JudgmentGroup Title="Order">
		<Para>
			<TJudge Position1="Accountant Member" Position2="None">
				Vikram
				Singh Yadav
			</TJudge>.—This is an appeal filed by the assessee against
			the order of the learned Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals)/National
			Faceless Appeal Centre, Delhi dated March 18, 2025 pertaining to the assessment
			year 2019-20.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>2.</Bold> At the outset, the learned authorised representative
			submitted that the assessee has moved a prayer for admission of
			the following additional ground of appeal :
		</Para>
		<Quote>
			<Para2>
				“Notwithstanding the original grounds of appeal, the
				reassessment proceedings initiated under section 148 of the Income-tax
				Act, 1961 are bad in law and void ab initio, as the notice under
				section 148 was issued by the jurisdictional Assessing Officer (JAO)
				instead of the National Faceless Assessment Centre (NFAC), which
				is in violation of the mandatory procedure prescribed under sections
				144B and 151A of the Act, vide notification Central Board of Direct
				Taxes Notification No. 18/2022/F. No. 370142/16/2022-TPL (Part 1) dated
				March 29, 2022 ([2022] 442 ITR (St.) 198) and as clarified by the
				hon’ble Punjab and Haryana High Court in the case of <Reference>
					<CRTo>
						<Title>Jatinder Singh Bhangu v. Union of India</Title>
					</CRTo>
				</Reference>
				<Footnote>3</Footnote> (W. P. No. 15745 of 2024, dated July 19,
				2024).”
			</Para2>
		</Quote>
		<Para>
			<Bold>3.</Bold> It was submitted that all the facts are borne
			out from the order of the Assessing Officer and no fresh facts are
			to be investigated and the additional ground being purely a legal
			ground, the same may be admitted in light of the decision of the
			hon’ble Supreme Court in the case of <Reference>
				<CRTo>
					<Title>
						National Thermal
						Power Co. Ltd. v. CIT
					</Title>
				</CRTo>
			</Reference><Footnote>4</Footnote>.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>4.</Bold> The learned Departmental representative has
			been heard who has not raised any specific objection for admission
			of the additional ground of appeal.
		</Para>
		<page no="757"></page>
		<Para>
			<Bold>5.</Bold> The additional ground so sought to be raised
			being purely legal in nature, the same is hereby admitted for necessary
			adjudication following the decision of the hon’ble Supreme Court
			in the case of <Reference>
				<CRTo>
					<Title>
						National Thermal Power Co.
						Ltd. v. CIT
					</Title>
				</CRTo>
			</Reference><Footnote>5</Footnote>
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>6.</Bold> In this regard, the learned authorised representative
			further submitted that basis certain information that the assessee
			has purchased certain immovable property and has made cash payment
			of Rs. 40,00,000, a show cause was issued under section 148A(b)
			of the Act by the Income-tax Officer, Ward-1, Nabha on March 2,
			2023 as to why notice under section 148 should not be issued on
			the basis of information that income chargeable to tax has escaped
			assessment. In response, the assessee filed her submission and thereafter, an order
			under section 148A(d) was passed on March 30, 2023 and on the same
			date, i. e., March 30, 2022, notice under section 148 was issued
			by Income-tax Officer, Ward, Nabha being the jurisdictional Assessing
			Officer.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>7.</Bold> It was submitted that the notice so issued
			under section 148 was in clear contravention of the mandatory requirement
			of faceless proceedings stipulated under the Income-tax Act post
			issuance of notification by the Ministry of Finance, Government
			of India dated March 29, 2022 under section 144B of the Act. It
			was submitted that after issuance of the said notification on March
			29, 2022, the notice under section 148 ought to have been issued
			by the Faceless Assessment Unit and not by the jurisdictional Assessing
			Officer. It was accordingly submitted that the notice so issued under
			section 148 has clearly been issued without jurisdiction. In this regard,
			our reference was drawn to the decision of co-ordinate Bench in the case
			of <Reference>
				<CRTo>
					<Title>Dy. CIT v. Aman Batra</Title>
				</CRTo>
			</Reference>
			<Footnote>6</Footnote> (I.
			T. A. No. 1040/Chand/2024 and C. O. No. 41/Chand/2024, dated May
			13, 2025), wherein the co-ordinate Bench following the decision
			of hon’ble Punjab and Haryana High Court has held that the notice
			issued under section 148 is bad in the eyes of law. In this regard,
			the relevant finding of the co-ordinate Bench read as under :
		</Para>
		<Quote>
			<Para2>
				“6. We have duly considered the rival contentions
				and gone through the record carefully. Admittedly, notice under
				section 148 was issued after the notification issued by the Ministry
				of Finance, Government of India on March 29, 2022. The notice under
				section 148 has been issued on March 29, 2023, i. e., almost one
				year from the notification. Thus, facts of other year are squarely
				applicable. The<page no="758"></page>issue in dispute is covered by the judgment of the
				hon’ble jurisdictional High Court which read as under :
			</Para2>
			<Para3>
				‘1. Challenge made through the instant petition is to the
				notice dated March 1, 2025 (annexure P1) issued to the petitioner
				by the respondents under section 148 of the Income-tax Act, 1961.
				The primary ground of challenge raised by the petitioner is that
				the impugned notice has been issued by the jurisdictional Assessing Officer
				which could not have been done because in terms of the notification
				dated March 29, 2022 (annexure P2), issued by the Ministry of Finance, Government
				of India, the impugned notice could have been issued only by way
				of faceless assessment.
			</Para3>
			<Para3>
				2. In support of his afore submission, the learned counsel
				for the petitioner places reliance on the following two judgments
				of this court :
			</Para3>
			<Para4>
				(i) C. W. P. No. 15745 of 2024, titled <Reference>
					<CRTo>
						<Title>
							Jatinder
							Singh Bhangu v. Union of India
						</Title>
					</CRTo>
				</Reference><Footnote>7</Footnote>,
				decided on July 19, 2024 ; and
			</Para4>
			<Para4>
				(ii) C. W. P. No. 21509 of 2023, titled <Reference>
					<CRTo>
						<Title>
							Jasjit
							Singh v. Union of India
						</Title>
					</CRTo>
				</Reference><Footnote>8</Footnote>,
				decided on July 29, 2024.
			</Para4>
			<Para3>
				3. The learned counsel for the respondents does not dispute
				the fact that the case of the petitioner is covered in his favour
				by the law laid down through the aforesaid two judgments rendered
				by two -different co-ordinate Benches of this court in <Reference>
					<CRTo>
						<Title>Jatinder Singh Bhangu v. Union of India</Title>
					</CRTo>
				</Reference>1 and
				<Reference>
					<CRTo>
						<Title>Jasjit Singh v. Union of India</Title>
					</CRTo>
				</Reference>2.
			</Para3>
			<Para3>
				4. In the light of the above, in terms of the law laid down
				in <Reference>
					<CRTo>
						<Title>Jatinder Singh Bhangu v. Union of India</Title>
					</CRTo>
				</Reference>1 and
				<Reference>
					<CRTo>
						<Title>Jasjit Singh v. Union of India</Title>
					</CRTo>
				</Reference>2 the
				impugned notice dated March 1, 2025 (annexure P1) issued by the jurisdictional
				Assessing Officer, is hereby quashed with liberty to the respondents
				to proceed against the petitioner in accordance with law.
			</Para3>
			<Para2>5. The petition is allowed in the above terms.’</Para2>
			<Para2>
				7. Respectfully following the judgment of the hon’ble High
				Court, we allow the ground of appeal of cross-objection and hold
				that notice issued under section 148 of the Income-tax Act in the assessment year
				2019-20 is bad in the eyes of law. It was without jurisdiction. Accordingly,
				reassessment order is quashed.
			</Para2>
			<page no="759"></page>
			<Para2>
				8. Though the Revenue has raised a number of issues on the
				merits in its appeal, but we have quashed the reassessment order,
				therefore, all the issues become academic in nature at this stage.
				We have quashed the assessment order on the strength of number of -judgments
				rendered by the hon’ble jurisdictional High Court, which is a view
				unanimously taken by other hon’ble High Courts also. Therefore,
				we do not deem it necessary to consider other issues on the merits.”
			</Para2>
		</Quote>
		<Para>
			<Bold>8.</Bold> Further, reference was drawn to another decision
			of a co-ordinate Bench in the case of <Reference>
				<CRTo>
					<Title>
						Bagga
						Singh v. Dy. CIT
					</Title>
				</CRTo>
			</Reference><Footnote>9</Footnote>, in I. T. A. No. 2318/Chand/2024,
			dated May 13, 2025 wherein similar view has been taken by the co-ordinate
			Chandigarh Benches.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>9.</Bold> The learned senior Departmental representative
			is heard who has fairly submitted that though there are decisions
			of the hon’ble Punjab and Haryana High Court, however, the Revenue
			is in appeal before the hon’ble Supreme Court against such decisions
			rendered by the hon’ble High Court. However, the learned senior
			Departmental representative has fairly -submitted that there is
			no stay which has been granted by the hon’ble Supreme Court against
			the decision rendered by the hon’ble Punjab and Haryana High Court.
			Further, he has relied on the orders of the lower authorities.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>10.</Bold> I have heard the rival contentions and perused
			the material available on the record. In the instant case, it is
			noted that the notice under section 148 has been issued on March
			30, 2023 by the Income-tax Officer, Ward, Nabha who is the jurisdictional
			Assessing Officer and not by the Faceless Assessment Unit. The said
			notice has been issued almost after a year from the issuance of
			notification by the Ministry of Finance, Government of India on
			March 29, 2022 requiring issuance of notice and conduct of assessment
			proceedings by the Faceless Assessment Unit. There is thus a clear
			breach of the binding notification so issued under section 144B requiring
			issuance of notices and conduct of proceedings through the Faceless
			Assessment Unit. The co-ordinate Bench in the case of <Reference>
				<CRTo>
					<Title>Dy. CIT v. Aman Batra</Title>
				</CRTo>
			</Reference><Footnote>10</Footnote> and thereafter in case of
			<Reference>
				<CRTo>
					<Title>Bagga Singh v. Dy. CIT (International Taxation)</Title>
				</CRTo>
			</Reference><Footnote>9</Footnote>has
			referred to the decision of the hon’ble jurisdictional High Court
			wherein the notice issued by the jurisdictional Assessing Officer
			has been quashed by the hon’ble Punjab and Haryana High Court and
			by following the same, it has been held that the notice so issued
			is bad in law. Nothing has been brought on record to deviate from
			the view so taken<page no="760"></page>by the co-ordinate Benches which in turn are guided
			by the decision of the hon’ble jurisdictional High Court. Respectfully
			following the -decision of hon’ble jurisdictional High Court which
			has been followed by the co-ordinate Benches in the decisions referred
			supra, the notice so issued on March 30, 2023 by the jurisdictional
			Assessing Officer, i. e., Income-tax Officer, Ward Nabha is clearly
			without jurisdiction and bad in law. In light of the same, the additional
			ground of appeal so taken by the assessee is hereby allowed.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>11.</Bold> In light of the aforesaid, the other grounds
			of appeal have become academic in nature and the same are left open
			and not adjudicated upon.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>12.</Bold> In the result, the appeal of the assessee
			is allowed.
		</Para>
		<Para>Order pronounced in the open court on August 18, 2025.</Para>
	</JudgmentGroup>
	<Footnotes>
		<Link>1</Link>
		<LinkCont>
			2025 SCC
			OnLine ITAT 9124.
		</LinkCont>
	</Footnotes>
	<Footnotes>
		<Link>2</Link>
		<LinkCont>[2022] 442 ITR (St.) 198.</LinkCont>
	</Footnotes>
	<Footnotes>
		<Link>3</Link>
		<LinkCont>
			[2024] 466 ITR 474 (P&amp;H) ; 2024 SCC OnLine P&amp;H
			9337.
		</LinkCont>
	</Footnotes>
	<Footnotes>
		<Link>4</Link>
		<LinkCont>
			[1998]
			229 ITR 383 (SC) ; [2003] 132 STC 566 (SC) ; (1997) 7 SCC 489 ;
			1996 SCC OnLine SC 173.
		</LinkCont>
	</Footnotes>
	<Footnotes>
		<Link>5</Link>
		<LinkCont>
			[1998] 229
			ITR 383 (SC) ; [2003] 132 STC 566 (SC) ; (1997) 7 SCC 489 ; 1996
			SCC OnLine SC 173.
		</LinkCont>
	</Footnotes>
	<Footnotes>
		<Link>6</Link>
		<LinkCont>2025 SCC OnLine ITAT 6348.</LinkCont>
	</Footnotes>
	<Footnotes>
		<Link>7</Link>
		<LinkCont>[2024] 466 ITR 474 (P&amp;H) ; 2024 SCC OnLine P&amp;H 9337.</LinkCont>
	</Footnotes>
	<Footnotes>
		<Link>8</Link>
		<LinkCont>[2024] 467 ITR 52 (P&amp;H) ; 2024 SCC OnLine P&amp;H 9677.</LinkCont>
	</Footnotes>
	<Footnotes>
		<Link>9</Link>
		<LinkCont>2025 SCC OnLine ITAT 6284.</LinkCont>
	</Footnotes>
	<Footnotes>
		<Link>10</Link>
		<LinkCont>
			2025
			SCC OnLine ITAT 6348.
		</LinkCont>
	</Footnotes>
</TCase>