<TCase ID="133 ITR (Trib) 0716" Shtitle="Nayara Energy Ltd. v. Asst. CIT (Mum)" Appendix="N">
	<CaseId>
		<Pagenum>
			<ShCourtName>(Mumbai)</ShCourtName>
		</Pagenum>
	</CaseId>
	<court>
		<CourtName>Income-tax Appellate Tribunal</CourtName>
		<Bench Special="n">
			Mumbai “B” Bench
		</Bench>
	</court>
	<CauseTitleGroup>
		<CauseTitle>
			<ApellantGroup>
				<Apellant Type="Apellant">
					Nayara Energy Ltd.<Footnote>1</Footnote>
					<Para>(On behalf of merged entity Vadinar Oil Terminal Ltd.)</Para>
				</Apellant>
			</ApellantGroup>
			<RespondentGroup>
				<Respondent>Assistant Commissioner of Income-tax</Respondent>
			</RespondentGroup>
		</CauseTitle>
	</CauseTitleGroup>
	<JudGroup>
		<TJudge Position1="Accountant Member" Position2="None">
			Prashant
			Maharishi
		</TJudge>
		<TJudge Position1="Judicial Member" Position2="None">
			Rahul Chaudhary
		</TJudge>
	</JudGroup>
	<Date Month="September" Date="11" Year="2024"/>
	<SRGroup>
		<Sr>
			<ActAbbr>ITA 1961,</ActAbbr>
			<SecNum> ss 28(i)</SecNum>
			<SecNum>36(1)(vii)</SecNum>
			<SecNum>(2)</SecNum>
			<SecNum>37(1)</SecNum>
			<SecNum/>
		</Sr>
	</SRGroup>
	<AssYearGroup>
		<AssYear>2017-18</AssYear>
	</AssYearGroup>
	<HFGroup>
		<Hf Favourof="Department"/>
		<Hf Favourof="Assessee"/>
		<Hf Favourof="Remanded"/>
	</HFGroup>
	<CWGroup>
		<CW>
			<Bold>A.</Bold>
		</CW>
		<CW>Income-tax</CW>
		<CW>Bad debt</CW>
		<CW>Business loss</CW>
		<CW>
			Loss
			on assignment of receivables and payables on inter-corporate deposits
			to sister concern
		</CW>
		<CW>
			Auditors’ qualified opinion regarding
			loss not given in respect of similar transaction with another group
			concern wherein no decrease shown in fair market value
		</CW>
		<CW>
			No
			justification for transfer of assets and liabilities for consideration
			as meagre as 2 per cent. of net value
		</CW>
		<CW>
			Assessee board’s resolution making
			no reference to loss on transfer or to valuation of inter-corporate
			deposits at fair market value or to whom assets transferred or which
			assets were to be sold to which entity or whether board perused
			draft agreement before executing it
		</CW>
		<CW>
			Agreement of transfer
			unsigned
		</CW>
		<CW>
			Non-production of board’s resolution and director‘s
			report going against assessee in -proving genuineness of transaction
			and in discharging onus
		</CW>
		<CW>
			No write-off of any irrecoverable
			amount
		</CW>
		<CW>Loss not claimable as bad debt</CW>
		<CW>
			Fulfilment
			of conditions of section <SecRef ID="ITA-1961-36-2">36(2)</SecRef> in
			reckoning interest income as income in computing profit for earlier years
			irrelevant
		</CW>
		<CW>
			Assessee’s balance-sheet showing payables and receivables
			as loans and advances, and loss as exceptional item
		</CW>
		<CW>
			Cash-flow
			statement showing loss as arising from investment, not operational,
			activities
		</CW>
		<CW>
			Investment in inter-corporate deposits not constituting
			assessee’s business
		</CW>
		<CW>
			Offering interest income as business
			income irrelevant to treat loss as being from investment since assessee
			treating investment activity as such,<page no="717"></page>not as business activity
		</CW>
		<CW>
			Assessee’s
			incidental or ancillary object of lending not business activity
			supporting main object of shipping and transportation
		</CW>
		<CW>
			Loss
			not on revenue, but on -capital, account
		</CW>
		<CW>
			Not constituting
			bad debt or business loss to qualify for deduction
		</CW>
		<CW>
			Held,
			Assessing Officer’s order upheld
		</CW>
		<CW>
			<ActName>Income-tax Act, 1961</ActName>,
			ss. <SecRef ID="ITA-1961-28-i">28(i)</SecRef>,
			<SecRef ID="ITA-1961-36-1-vii">36(1)(vii)</SecRef>,
			<SecRef ID="ITA-1961-36-2">36(2)</SecRef>,
			<SecRef ID="ITA-1961-115JB">115JB</SecRef>.
		</CW>
	</CWGroup>

	<CWGroup>
		<CW>
			<Bold>B.</Bold>
		</CW>
		<CW>Income-tax</CW>
		<CW>Business expenditure</CW>
		<CW>
			Interest
			on borrowed capital
		</CW>
		<CW>Advances to sister concern</CW>
		<CW>
			No
			evidence of commercial expediency shown
		</CW>
		<CW>
			Assessee using borrowed
			funds not for business purpose but to advance interest-free to group -concern
		</CW>
		<CW>
			Held, Assessing Officer’s order disallowing interest expenditure
			upheld
		</CW>
		<CW>
			<ActName>Income-tax Act, 1961</ActName>, ss.
			<SecRef ID="ITA-1961-36-1-vii">36(1)(vii)</SecRef>,
			<SecRef ID="ITA-1961-37-1">37(1)</SecRef>.
		</CW>
	</CWGroup>

	<CWGroup>
		<CW>
			<Bold>C.</Bold>
		</CW>
		<CW>Income-tax</CW>
		<CW>Business expenditure</CW>
		<CW>
			Interest
			on borrowed capital
		</CW>
		<CW>Investment made in group concern</CW>
		<CW>
			No
			business -activity in investee company
		</CW>
		<CW>
			Loss incurred in
			investment with additional finance cost
		</CW>
		<CW>
			Assessee submitting
			additional -evidence by way of investee’s annual accounts, bank
			borrowings and note of board of directors
		</CW>
		<CW>
			Matter restored
			to Assessing Officer with direction to assessee to substantiate
			interest expenditure
		</CW>
		<CW>
			Assessing Officer to also examine whether
			assessee had any interest in -making investment in sister concern
			before deciding allowability of interest expenditure
		</CW>
		<CW>
			<ActName>
				Income-tax
				Act, 1961
			</ActName>, ss. <SecRef ID="ITA-1961-36-1-vii">36(1)(vii)</SecRef>,
			<SecRef ID="ITA-1961-37-1">37(1)</SecRef>.
		</CW>
	</CWGroup>

	<CWGroup>
		<CW>
			<Bold>D.</Bold>
		</CW>
		<CW>Income-tax</CW>
		<CW>Deduction of tax at source</CW>
		<CW>
			Non-granting
			of credit
		</CW>
		<CW>
			Matter remanded to Assessing Officer to verify
			issue on merits before granting credit
		</CW>
		<CW>
			<ActName>
				Income-tax
				Act, 1961
			</ActName>.
		</CW>
	</CWGroup>

	<?Fm Condstart FM8_SYSTEM_HIDEELEMENT?>
	<CSGroup hidden="y">
		<CS>Income-tax</CS>
		<CS>Bad debt</CS>
		<CS>Business loss</CS>
		<CS>Business expenditure</CS>
		<CS>Interest on borrowed capital</CS>
		<CS>Deduction of tax at source</CS>
	</CSGroup>
	<?Fm Condend FM8_SYSTEM_HIDEELEMENT?>
	<HeadNote>
		<Para>
			For assessment year <AssYear>2017-18</AssYear>,
			the case of the assessee-company, engaged in the business of crude
			oil and petroleum products, was selected for scrutiny by -issue
			of notice under sections <SecRef ID="ITA-1961-143-2">143(2)</SecRef> and
			<SecRef ID="ITA-1961-142-1">142(1)</SecRef> of the <ActName>
				Income-tax
				Act, 1961
			</ActName>, following its declaration of loss and computation
			of book profit under section <SecRef ID="ITA-1961-115JB">115JB</SecRef> at
			a loss in its return of income. Thereafter, the assessment order
			was passed under section <SecRef ID="ITA-1961-143-3">143(3)</SecRef> assessing
			a positive income, the book profit -remaining unchanged. The Commissioner
			(Appeals) dismissed the assessee’s appeal.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			The assessee challenged the following issues : disallowance
			of loss on -account of assignment of certain receivables and payables
			to its group -concern IA pursuant to valuation and reassessment
			of its ability to collect such amount ; partial disallowance of
			interest expenses claimed in excess of interest income earned on
			inter-corporate deposits ; disallowance of interest<page no="718"></page>expenses incurred
			for the loan taken for investment in EL ; and short-granting of
			credit for tax deducted at source.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			The assessee had sold receivables and payables of inter-corporate
			deposits from its parent E group of companies to its sister concern,
			IA, resulting in loss which it claimed as a deduction. The Assessing
			Officer held the transaction to be sham and the loss fictitious,
			not allowable as a bad debt or business loss.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			The assessee had incurred interest expenses and also earned
			interest -income. No interest had been charged on certain deposits
			for reasons of -commercial expediency. The Commissioner (Appeals)
			categorically noted that on the question whether the funds borrowed
			were used for business -purposes, no details were furnished by the
			assessee.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			The assessee had made investment in company EL, which it claimed
			was meant for EL to carry out trading activity. However, no such
			activity could be carried out because of prevalent market conditions.
			These shares were brought back from the assessee resulting in a
			loss to the assessee. Over and above the loss, the assessee had
			also debited finance cost in its books of account incurred towards
			this investment. Before the Assessing Officer, no document in relation
			thereto was produced and the record showed that no business -happened
			in EL. Therefore, the Assessing Officer held that as nothing was brought
			on record to prove that the investment was in relation to the assessee’s
			business, he disallowed the interest expenditure, which the Commissioner (Appeals)
			confirmed.
		</Para>
		<Para>On appeal by the assessee :</Para>
		<Para>
			<EmphasisR>Held</EmphasisR>, partly allowing the appeal, (i)
			that the additional evidence submitted by the assessee with respect
			to the board note relating to the investment in its subsidiary company,
			audited financial statements of the subsidiary and board resolution
			of assignment of receivables and payables, was to be admitted since the
			main reason for the disallowance was on account of interest expenditure on
			investment made in the subsidiary. <EmphasisR>(para 11)</EmphasisR>
		</Para>
		<Para2>
			(ii) That although the auditors had given a qualified opinion
			regarding the loss in the transaction of assignment of receivables
			and payables to IA, there was no such qualification made by them
			with respect to transaction of sale of similar assets and liabilities
			with respect to another sister concern, ESJ, in which case there
			was no decrease in the fair market value of even a -single rupee.
			Whereas on the receivables transferred to IA, loss was recorded. Both
			the cases were of companies falling under the same holding company. Thus,
			there was no justification for transfer to sister concern IA of
			assets and liabilities for a meagre consideration representing about
			2 per cent. of the net<page no="719"></page>asset value thereof. Further, in the resolution
			passed by the assessee, there was no reference of any loss incurred
			in the transfer of the asset, or valuation of inter-corporate deposits
			at fair market value, or to whom these assets were to be sold, or
			which assets were to be sold to which entity, or whether the draft agreement
			had been perused by the Board before entering into the transaction. Further,
			the agreement with IA for transfer of receivables by the assessee
			was an unsigned document. Therefore, the production of the board
			resolution did not help the assessee’s case. The assessee also stated
			that the director’s report, referred in the annual report, was not
			accessible to it and, therefore, could not be produced. The non-production
			of such a document went against the assessee in proving the genuineness
			of transaction, the onus of which lay on the -assessee. There was
			no reason to deviate from the orders of the lower authorities.
			<EmphasisR>(paras 44, 45, 47, 50, 52, 53, 54, 55)</EmphasisR>
		</Para2>
		<Para2>
			(iii) That regarding the assessee’s claim that it should
			be allowed the -deduction of the loss as bad debts written off under
			section <SecRef ID="ITA-1961-36-1-vii">36(1)(vii)</SecRef>, there was
			no write-off of any irrecoverable amount. The loss on sale or transfer
			of certain payables and receivables could not be claimed as bad
			debt. The assessee’s argument that it had fulfilled the conditions
			of section <SecRef ID="ITA-1961-36-2">36(2)</SecRef> in reckoning the
			interest income as income while computing the profit for earlier
			years, was not relevant. Therefore, the assessee was not entitled
			to claim the deduction of bad debt written off in its books of account
			under section <SecRef ID="ITA-1961-36-1-vii">36(1)(vii)</SecRef> since
			there was no write-off of bad debt. <EmphasisR>(para 57)</EmphasisR>
		</Para2>
		<Para2>
			(iv) That as regards the assessee’s claim to treat the loss
			as a trading loss, a study of the assessee’s balance-sheet showed
			the payables and receivables treated as loans and advances and the
			amount of loss incurred was shown as an exceptional item and in
			the cash flow statement, it was shown to be from investing, not
			operating, activities. Therefore, it was apparent that it was not the
			assessee’s business to make investment in inter-corporate deposits.
			As a result, the loss was not allowable as a business loss. There
			was also no force in the assessee’s contention that it had offered
			the interest income as business income and, therefore, the investment
			should be considered as a business -activity for the simple reason
			that the investment was held by the assessee to be an investment
			activity. While the assessee’s main object was shipping and transportation,
			its incidental or ancillary activity of lending was not a business
			activity to support its main object. Thus, the assessee’s loss was
			not on revenue, but on capital, account, not constituting a business
			loss to qualify for deduction. There was no infirmity in the Assessing
			Officer’s order to deny deduction of the loss holding the transaction
			to be sham and intended to book<page no="720"></page>fictitious loss, rendering it non-deductible
			as either bad debt or business loss. <EmphasisR>(paras 58, 59, 60)</EmphasisR>
		</Para2>
		<Para2>
			(v) That regarding disallowance of interest expenditure,
			no evidence of commercial expediency was submitted. The assessee
			had used borrowed funds, not for business purpose, but for advancing
			to its sister concern without charging any interest. In view of
			this, there was no infirmity in the order of the lower authorities
			disallowing interest expenditure under section
			<SecRef ID="ITA-1961-36-1-iii">36(1)(iii)</SecRef>. <EmphasisR>
				(para
				69)
			</EmphasisR>
		</Para2>
		<Para2>
			(vi) That the assessee submitted EL’s annual accounts as
			well as the -borrowings made from bankers for such investment. These
			were additional evidence along with the note of the board of directors,
			which were admitted. Therefore, this evidence needed to be examined
			by the Assessing Officer. As a result, the matter was restored back
			to the Assessing Officer with direction to the assessee to substantiate
			the interest expenditure incurred by it on the -investment made
			in EL as an allowable deduction. The Assessing Officer would also
			need to determine whether the assessee had any interest in carrying out
			the transaction by examining the accounts of EL and the sanctioned -letters
			of the banks before deciding the issue of allowability of the interest -expenditure.
			<EmphasisR>(para 76)</EmphasisR>
		</Para2>
		<Para2>
			(vii) That the assessee was directed to substantiate its
			claim of credit for tax deduction at source not granted to it, before
			the Assessing Officer, who was to decide the issue after verification
			on its merits. <EmphasisR>(para 77)</EmphasisR>
		</Para2>
		<Para>
			<Italics>Chronological list of cases cited 		on page(s)</Italics>
		</Para>
		<Referred>
			<CRT>
				<Citation Citation="439 ITR 399" year="2021" Court="Bom" fbsb="0"/> ; <Citothers>2021 SCC OnLine Bom 14059</Citothers>,
				<Title>
					CIT (Pr.) v. Mahindra Engineering and Chemical Products Ltd.
				</Title> 		735a-b
			</CRT>
			<CRT>
				<Citothers>[2015] 63 taxmann.com 283 (Bom)</Citothers>, <Title>
					CIT v. Pudumjee
					Pulp and
					Paper Mills Ltd.
				</Title> 		734e
			</CRT>
			<CRT>
				<Citation Citation="342 ITR 285" year="2012" Court="Bom" fbsb="0"/> ; <Citothers>2012 SCC OnLine Bom 296</Citothers>,
				<Title>
					CIT v.
					Shreyas S. Morakhia
				</Title> 		734f
			</CRT>
			<CRT>
				<Citation Citation="288 ITR 1" year="2007" Court="SC" fbsb="0"/> ;
				<Citothers>(2007) 1 SCC 781</Citothers> ; <Citothers>
					2006 SCC OnLine
					SC 1411
				</Citothers>, <Title>S. A. Builders Ltd. v. CIT (Appeals)</Title> 		725h,
				752f-g
			</CRT>
			<CRT>
				<Citation Citation="220 ITR 185" year="1996" Court="SC" fbsb="0"/> ;
				<Citothers>(1996) 9 SCC 25</Citothers> ; <Citothers>
					1996 SCC OnLine
					SC 140
				</Citothers>, <Title>Veecumsees v. CIT</Title> 		749b
			</CRT>
			<CRT>
				<Citation Citation="119 ITR 380" year="1979" Court="Bom" fbsb="0"/> ; <Citothers>1976 SCC OnLine Bom 197</Citothers>,
				<Title>
					CIT v.
					Investa Industrial Corporation Ltd.
				</Title> 		732g
			</CRT>
			<CRT>
				<Citation Citation="38 ITR 413" year="1960" Court="Mad" fbsb="0"/> ;
				<Citothers>1959 SCC OnLine Mad 229</Citothers>, <Title>
					Mir Mohd.
					Ali v. CIT
				</Title> 		747a
			</CRT>
			<CRT>
				<Citothers>(I. T. A. No. 777/Mum/2022, dated October 10, 2022)</Citothers>,
				<Title>
					Nayara
					Energy Ltd. v. Asst. CIT
				</Title> 		748g, 750a
			</CRT>
			<page no="721"></page>
			<CRT>
				<Citothers>
					(M. A. No. 332/Mum/2022 in I. T. A. No. 777/Mum/2022,
					dated February 6, 2023)
				</Citothers>, <Title>
					Nayara Energy Ltd. v. Asst.
					CIT
				</Title>748h, 750b
			</CRT>
		</Referred>
		<TaxCaseNo>
			<Ref>I. T. A. No.</Ref>
			<Caseno>
				<Number>778</Number>/Mum/
				<year>2022</year> (assessment year <AssYear>2017-18</AssYear>).
			</Caseno>
		</TaxCaseNo>
		<CounselGroup>
			<forApellant>
				<CounselName>Nitesh Joshi</CounselName>,
				Advocate and <CounselName>Sagar Devani</CounselName>, Chartered
				Accountant, for the assessee.
			</forApellant>
			<forRespondent>
				<CounselName>S. Srinivasu</CounselName>, Commissioner
				of Income-tax--Departmental representative, for the Department.
			</forRespondent>
		</CounselGroup>
	</HeadNote>
	<JudgmentGroup Title="Order">
		<Para>The order of the Bench was pronounced by</Para>
		<Para>
			<TJudge Position1="Accountant Member" Position2="None">
				Prashant
				Maharishi
			</TJudge>.—This appeal is filed by Nayara Energy Ltd. (on
			behalf of merged entities Vadinar Oil Terminal Ltd. (VOTL) for the
			assessment year 2017-18 against the appellate order passed by the
			Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals)-48, Mumbai (the learned “CIT(A)”)
			dated February 25, 2022, wherein appeal filed by the assessee against
			the assessment order passed by the Assistant Commissioner of Income-tax,
			Circle-14 (3)(1), Mumbai (the “AO”) on December 28, 2019 under section
			143(3) of the Income-tax Act, 1961 (the “Act”), wherein the total
			income of the assessee returned at a loss of Rs. 20,39,79,700 and
			book profit computed at a loss of Rs. 8,82,22,43,600 was assessed
			at as income of Rs. 1,68,17,76,090 and book profit at loss of Rs. 8,82,22,43,600,
			was dismissed.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>2.</Bold> The assessee aggrieved with the same has raised
			following grounds of appeal :
		</Para>
		<Quote>
			<Para2>
				<Italics>
					Disallowance of loss on account of assignment
					of certain receivables and payable is pursuant to valuation and
					reassessment of companies’ ability to collect the amount of Rs.
					2,51,30,00,000
				</Italics>
			</Para2>
			<Para3>
				1. On the facts and in the circumstances of the case, the
				Learned Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals)-48 and the learned
				Assessing Officer erred on the facts and in law in disallowing loss
				of Rs. 2,51,30,00,000 actually incurred during the year up on assignment of
				identified receivables and payable is comprising inter-corporate deposits,
				interest thereon, security deposits, other receivables, and payable
				is from or to Essar group entities based on incorrect facts and surmises.
				The appellant submits that the net losses incurred on assignment
				of receivables and payable is based on a detailed evaluation by
				an independent valuer are deductible under section 36(1)(vii) of
				the Income-tax Act, 1961 (the “Act”).
			</Para3>
			<page no="722"></page>
			<Para3>
				2. The learned Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals) and the learned
				Assessing Officer erred in rejecting the alternate claim of the deductibility
				of the loss on assignment under section 28(i) of the Act on the
				basis that the loss was not incidental to the business but was a future
				anticipated loss, disregarding the appellant’s regular activity
				of taking and giving ICD is in line with the object clause of the -memorandum
				of association (MOA). The learned Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals)
				and the learned Assessing Officer further erred in not appreciating
				that this loss was actually incurred ahead of its holding company
				being taken over by the third parties and should be allowed as a
				business loss.
			</Para3>
			<Para3>
				The appellant prays that the adjustment in relation to disallowance
				of loss on account of company’s ability to amount specified amount
				of Rs. 251.30 crores by the learned Assessing Officer and upheld
				by the learned Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals) be deleted.
			</Para3>
			<Para2>
				<Italics>
					Partial disallowance of interest expenses claimed
					in excess of interest income earned on inter-corporate deposits
					Rs. 1,58,12,00,000.
				</Italics>
			</Para2>
			<Para3>
				3. The learned Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals) and the learned
				Assessing Officer erred on facts and in law impartially -disallowing
				interest expenses in excess of interest income earned amounting
				to Rs. 158 of blacks on the basis of irrelevant and erroneous observations
				and conjectures, without appreciating the fact that the interest
				expenses, incurred for the purposes, and in the course of business,
				is allowable under section 36(1)(iii) of the Act and the business
				expediency of such interest cannot be determined on the basis of
				quantum incurred. The appellant submits that the entire amount of
				interest expenses of Rs. 253.30 crores be allowed as claimed, without
				restricting the amount of interest income of Rs. 95.38 crores and
				during the year.
			</Para3>
			<Para3>
				4. Without prejudice to the above, the learned Commissioner
				of Income-tax (Appeals) and the learned Assessing Officer erred
				in -disallowing the interest expenses on ICD is being a business
				expenditure under section 37(1) of the Act.
			</Para3>
			<Para3>
				5. The learned Assessing Officer erred in considering the
				interest income from ICD is under the head “Income from other sources” instead
				of considering the same under the head “Profits and gains of business
				and profession” in complete disregard of the fact that the appellant
				was carrying on a systematic and continuous business activity of
				taking ICD is an giving ICD is and is assessable under the head<page no="723"></page>“Profits
				and gains of business or profession”. The appellant submits that
				the interest income arising from its regular business activity,
				be assessed as profits and gains from business or profession as
				was done in the prior assessment years.
			</Para3>
			<Para3>
				The appellant prays that the adjustment made by the learned Assessing
				Officer and upheld by the learned Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals)
				in respect of partial disallowance of interest expenses claimed
				in excess of interest income on ICD is to be deleted.
			</Para3>
			<Para2>
				<Italics>
					Disallowance of interest expenses incurred for the
					loan taken for investment in Ennegaon Ltd., Mauritius, Rs. 1,71,57,00,000
				</Italics>
			</Para2>
			<Para3>
				6. The learned Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals) and the learned
				Assessing Officer erred in on the facts and in law in disallowing
				interest expenses incurred on financial assistance obtained from
				banks for making strategic equity investment in foreign -company,
				completely overlooking the facts and circumstances relating to the
				investment. The appellant submits that the interest, being squarely
				covered under the specific provisions of section 36(1)(iia) be held
				as deductible as claimed.
			</Para3>
			<Para3>
				7. Without prejudice to the above, the learned Commissioner
				of Income-tax (Appeals) and the learned Assessing Officer erred
				on facts and in law in not allowing the interest expenses incurred -formation
				investment for furtherance of business of the appellant under section
				37(1) of the Act.
			</Para3>
			<Para3>
				The appellant prays that the adjustment made by the learned Assessing
				Officer and upheld by the learned Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals)
				pertaining to the disallowance of interest expenses incurred for
				the loan taken for investment in Ennegaon Ltd., Mauritius be deleted.
			</Para3>
			<Para2>
				<Italics>Grant of short TDS credit of Rs. 2.29 crores</Italics>
			</Para2>
			<Para3>
				8. The learned Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals) and the learned
				Assessing Officer erred on the facts and in law in not/short granting
				of TDS credit of Rs. 2.29 crores while determining the refund of
				the appellant for the year.
			</Para3>
			<Para3>
				The appellant prays that the TDS credit should be granted
				of Rs. 2.29 crores while computing the refund which was not granted
				by the learned Assessing Officer and upheld by the learned Commissioner
				of Income-tax (Appeals).
			</Para3>
			<page no="724"></page>
			<Para2>
				<Italics>
					Order bad in law in the absence of an opportunity
					for personal hearing
				</Italics>
			</Para2>
			<Para3>
				9. The learned Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals) order
				in passing the order without providing an opportunity of personal
				hearing though requested by the appellant.
			</Para3>
			<Para3>
				The appellant prays that the order being passed in violation
				of principles of natural justice and against the provisions of the Income-tax
				Act, 1961 is bad in law and should be quashed.
			</Para3>
		</Quote>
		<Para>
			<Bold>3.</Bold> Fact shows that the assessee is a company
			engaged in the business of handling crude oil and petroleum products.
			Its facility consists of an offshore single-point mooring, two jetties
			for handling liquid petroleum -products, tanks for storage of crude
			oil and petroleum products and rail and road gantries for dispatch
			of petroleum products.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>4.</Bold> The assessee filed its return of income on
			February 8, 2018 declaring a total loss of Rs. 203,979,700 and computed
			the book profit under section 115JB at a loss of Rs. 8,822,243,600.
			The return of income was picked up for scrutiny by issue of notice
			under section 143(2) of the act on August 27, 2018 and further notice
			under section 142(1) of the Act was also issued.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>5.</Bold> After scrutiny, the assessment order was passed
			under section 143(3) of the Act on December 28, 2019, wherein the
			total income of the assessee was assessed at Rs. 5,605,920,300 and
			the book profit remained unchanged.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>6.</Bold> Against this, the assessee preferred an appeal
			before the learned Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals), wherein
			appellate order was passed on February 25, 2022 dismissing the appeal
			of the assessee. Therefore, the assessee is in appeal before us.
			Before us the assessee has filed a rectified form 36 which is taken
			on record.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>7.</Bold> The assessee has also made an application
			for admission of additional evidence and filed a paper book starting
			from page Nos. 629-914 (paper book-III) as additional evidence containing
			eighteen documents. Out of that it was stated that thirteen documents
			are already part of Departmental records however not submitted during
			the assessment proceedings for assessment year 2017-18. With respect
			to documents mentioned at serial No. 14 is a memorandum of association
			of the company, board note relating to investments in Enneagon Ltd.
			Mauritius (serial No. 15), audited financial statements of Enneagon
			Ltd. Mauritius (serial No. 16) and board resolution for assignment
			of receivables and payable (serial No. 17) are the additional evidence.
			At serial No. 18 the assessee has submitted the computation of income
			for the assessment year 2017-18. With respect to serial Nos. 1 to
			13<page no="725"></page>the contention of the assessee was that about documents are part Departmental
			records for the respective assessment years and the Assessing Officer
			has relied on the same in the assessment order for the assessment year
			2017-18. The same are now being relied upon by the assessee-company
			to substantiate that interest income on inter-corporate deposits
			given by the appellant were offered to tax in respective years in
			return of income as business income and have been assessed also
			as business income. -Further for documents at serial No. 14 the
			assessee submitted that one of the objects of the assessee under
			the head objects incidental or ancillary to the attainment of the
			more main objects in its memorandum of association which allows
			the assessee to lend money. The said fact was mentioned by the assessee
			in its submission however neither the Assessing Officer nor the
			Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals) has called for the copy of
			this document and therefore the assessee wants to rely on the same
			to -substantiate its submission. With respect to documents at serial
			Nos. 15 and 16 it referred to the board note relating to investment
			in Ennagoan Ltd., Mauritius discusses and details on the proposal
			relating to availing of financing facility of US$ 450 million and
			use of proceeds for equity infusion into overseas subsidiary and
			audited financials of the said subsidiary for the year-ended March
			31, 2017. Both these documents are relied upon by the assessee to
			demonstrate the business rational and the business activity -carried
			out by that subsidiary for the year-ended March 31, 2017. With respect
			to document at serial No. 17 which is a board resolution relating
			to assignment is to demonstrate that the competent authority of
			the appellant has taken the decision regarding the said transaction
			after taking into account the larger scheme of things. It was the
			claim of the assessee that the above documents are relevant documents
			which could not have been furnished before the lower authorities
			and therefore those documents must be admitted deciding the issue.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>8.</Bold> The learned authorised representative pressed
			for its admission whereas the learned Departmental representative
			opposed its admission.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>9.</Bold> The learned authorised representative submitted
			that submissions were made before the learned Commissioner of Income-tax
			(Appeals) on February 18, 2021 which is placed at page No. 307—onwards
			wherein at page No. 316 the assessee has cited the decision of the
			honourable Supreme Court in the case of <Reference>
				<CRTo>
					<Title>
						S.
						A. Builders Ltd. v. CIT (Appeals)
					</Title>
				</CRTo>
			</Reference><Footnote>2</Footnote> and -further at page No. 317 the assessee
			has submitted that the assessee needs time before the learned Commissioner
			of Income-tax (Appeals) of 10-15 days further to supplement the
			above submission in view of the statutory<page no="726"></page>time line to file the
			return of income for the assessment year 2020-21 was approaching
			on February 15, 2021 and further the appellant has filed -several
			VSV applications for earlier years which were required for to -frequently
			visit tax office to clear pending rectification orders and order -giving
			effects. Under these circumstances considering that due to covid-19 related
			restrictions, the assessee wanted further time. Therefore, it was submitted
			that the assessee could not submit the detail. As this was the sufficient
			cause for not adducing these details before the learned lower authorities,
			now it should be admitted.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>10.</Bold> The learned Departmental representative vehemently
			objected to the same and submitted that the learned Commissioner
			of Income-tax (Appeals) has disposed of the appeal of the assessee
			on February 25, 2022. The assessee is relying on his letter dated
			February 18, 2021 wherein the assessee is seeking time. He submits
			that the assessee has made a further submission on November 8, 2021
			before the learned Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals), wherein
			once again the assessee has sought time of 10 days. He further submitted
			that since November 8, 2021 to February 25, 2022, four months’ time
			was available with the assessee, but nothing was submitted before
			the learned Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals). Therefore, the
			claim of the assessee is that no time was granted to the assessee
			by the learned Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals) for -submission
			of the additional evidence is devoid of any merit and is an incorrect
			statement. He submits that these is no reason given for non--submission
			before the learned Assessing Officer. Hence, he submitted that additional
			evidence should not be admitted as no sufficient cause is shown by the assessee.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>11.</Bold> We have carefully considered the rival contention
			and find that these documents are relevant for the assessee to demonstrate
			its case before the Tribunal for effective disposal of the grounds
			raised. It is undoubtedly clear that on February 18, 2021 the assessee
			has sought time before the learned Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals)
			for furnishing further information. Further another letter dated
			November 8, 2021 was once again submitted before the learned Commissioner
			of Income-tax (Appeals), in the last line itself the assessee has
			also sought 10 days’ time to supplement the above submission. The appellate
			order was passed on February 25, 2022. Thus, it is evident that the assessee
			has been given enough opportunities to submit the details. There
			is no reason stated that why these documents were not submitted
			before the learned Assessing Officer. However, we find that the additional
			evidence starting from serial Nos. 1-13 are with respect to the return
			of income and computation for the earlier years. The only additional<page no="727"></page>evidence
			that has been submitted by the assessee is with respect to the board note
			relating to investment in subsidiary company, audited financial statement
			of the subsidiary company and board resolution of assignment of
			receivable and payable. We find that the board note relating to
			investment in subsidiary and its annual accounts are the main reason
			for which the disallowance has been made on account of interest
			expenditure on investment made in subsidiary. Therefore, to decide
			that issue, these -documents are as such required by the authorities.
			In view of this, we admit the additional evidence furnished.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>12.</Bold> The first ground of appeal is with respect
			to disallowance of loss on account of assignment of certain receivables
			and payables pursuant to -valuation and reassessment of the company’s
			ability to collect the amount of Rs. 2,51,30,00,000.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>13.</Bold> Issue is that the assessee has sold ICD receivables
			from Essar group companies of Rs. 955 crores along with the Essar group
			ICD payable of Rs. 699 crores having net asset value of Rs. 256
			crores is transferred to a sister concern (fellow subsidiary) at
			Rs 4.98 crores, resulting in to loss of Rs. 251.30 crores. This
			loss is claimed as deduction by the assessee.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>14.</Bold> The brief facts of the grounds are dealt
			with by the learned Assessing Officer in paragraph No. 4 of the
			assessment order and by the learned Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals)
			in paragraph No. 5 of the appellate order.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>15.</Bold> The learned Assessing Officer has noted as
			under :
		</Para>
		<Quote>
			<Para2>
				”4.1 During the year under consideration the assessee
				has declared earnings before exceptional items and tax at Rs. 347.5
				crores. The assessee has claimed Rs. 918.68 crores as exceptional
				items due to which its profit before tax shrinks to a loss of Rs.
				570.83 crores.
			</Para2>
			<Para2>
				4.2 It is seen from the notes to accounts, item 40 deals
				with the exceptional items. The assessee was asked to provide details
				of such expenses vide notice under section 142(1), dated November
				11, 2019. Vide its submissions dated December 6, 2019, the assessee
				has -provided details of such expenses claimed in the profit and
				loss account.
			</Para2>
			<Para2>
				4.3 Item 40(a) to the notes deals with the ‘debit to profit
				or loss on reassessment of the company’s ability to collect the
				amount specified in note 56. The amount debited towards this head
				is Rs. 177.50 crores. It is further seen that this amount has not
				been added back to the total income of the assessee. The assessee
				was show caused to explain<page no="728"></page>why such amount should not be added back
				to the total income of the assessee.
			</Para2>
			<Para2>
				4.4 Vide submissions dated December 11, 2019 the assessee
				has provided the following explanation :
			</Para2>
			<Para3>
				‘Pursuant to the agreement between the company and Ibrox -Aviation
				and Trading P. Ltd. (IAPL) certain identified assets and -liabilities
				comprising of ICDs, security deposits, other receivables, interest
				on ICDs and payables from/to the Essar group were assigned to Ibrox
				Aviation and Trading P. Ltd. In view of the same, VOTL received
				an amount of Rs. 4.79 crores from IAPL as a consideration for transfer
				of net value of identified assets and liability (copy of agreement
				attached herewith).
			</Para3>
			<Para3>
				Pursuant to the said agreement, the company incurred one-time exceptional
				loss of Rs. 177.54 crores (net of expected credit loss (ECL) of
				Rs. 73.80 crores) for the year which has been accounted in the books
				of account as under :<Table>
					<TBody>
						<Row>
							<Entry>
								<Para>Particulars</Para>
							</Entry>
							<Entry>
								<Para>Amount in (Rs. in cr.)</Para>
							</Entry>
						</Row>
						<Row>
							<Entry>
								<Para>
									David to profit of loss on reassessment of the company’s ability
									to collect the amount specified
								</Para>
							</Entry>
							<Entry>
								<Para>251.30</Para>
							</Entry>
						</Row>
						<Row>
							<Entry>
								<Para>Less : ECL</Para>
							</Entry>
							<Entry>
								<Para>(73.80)</Para>
							</Entry>
						</Row>
						<Row>
							<Entry>
								<Para>Net charge to exceptional item</Para>
							</Entry>
							<Entry>
								<Para>177.50</Para>
							</Entry>
						</Row>
					</TBody>
				</Table>
			</Para3>
			<Para2>
				4.5 The assessee further goes on to explain the allowability
				of -various items mentioned in the assignment agreement as per the Income-tax
				Act. The submission of the assessee is discussed below :
			</Para2>
			<Para3>
				‘<Italics>Loss on transfer of ICDs and interest thereon :</Italics>
			</Para3>
			<Para4>
				Section 36(1)(vii) of the Act provides that subject to the
				provisions of section 36(2) of the Act, the amount of bad debt which
				is written off as irrecoverable in the accounts of the assessee
				shall be allowed as a deduction in computing business income. Further, -section
				36(2) of the Act provides the condition for claiming deduction under
				section 36(1) of the Act, inter alia, including :
			</Para4>
			<Para5>
				• Debt or part thereof in respect of which deduction is -proposed
				to be claimed should be taken into account in computing the income
				of the assessee of the previous year in which this amount of such
				debt or part thereof is written off or of an earlier year, or
			</Para5>
			<Para5>
				• Debt or part thereof in respect of which deduction is -proposed
				to be claimed represents money lent in the ordinary course of business
				of money lending under section 36(1)(vii) of the Act.
			</Para5>
			<page no="729"></page>
			<Para3>
				In the case of the company, the loss of assignment, inter
				alia, includes ICDs and interest on ICDs. The interest on ICDs have
				been offered to tax as business income in previous years. Consequently, based
				on the provisions of the law and fact of our case, this amount is clearly
				allowable as a deduction.’
			</Para3>
			<Para2>
				4.5.2 The submissions made by the assessee in relation to
				loss on transfer of ICDs and interest thereon have been perused.
				As per the assessee’s own submissions vide submissions dated September
				12, 2019, the assessee’s business is that of integrated oil terminal
				situated at Vadinar, Gujarat.
			</Para2>
			<Para2>
				It has a capacity of 58 MMTPA and handles crude oil and petroleum
				products. These facilities cater to provide services only to Nayara
				Energy Ltd. (formerly known as Essar Oil Ltd.).
			</Para2>
			<Para2>
				4.5.3 The assessee is taking refuge only on the thin ground
				that in earlier year it has recognised interest income as business
				income. Hence, it may be construed to be in money lending business.
				The -surmise of the assessee is not acceptable. To put things in
				perspective the following facts should be noted :
			</Para2>
			<Para3>
				1. The assessee-Vadinar Ports and Terminals Ltd (VPTL) and Vadinar
				Oil Terminal Ltd. (VOTL) has received inter-corporate deposits (ICD)
				from Essar Oil and Essar Ports Ltd. in earlier years. The funds
				out of these ICDs are advanced as ICDs to Essar group companies,
				which are shareholder or subsidiaries of Essar Oil.
			</Para3>
			<Para3>
				2. That for many years interest payments against ICD were accrued
				but not paid and stood in the books as payable.
			</Para3>
			<Para3>
				3. No business rational has been submitted by the assessee
				for taking ICDs from a company and advancing it to the shareholders/subsidiaries
				of that same company, suggesting that these transactions are not
				out of usual business transaction.
			</Para3>
			<Para3>
				4. Inter-corporate deposits are instruments in which, the
				initiation is at the instance of the depositor, i. e., the giver
				who has surplus funds, as against in the case of a loan where the
				transaction is -initiated at the instance of the borrower who is
				in need of the money. Further in the case of an ICD, the amount
				is repayable on demand whereas a loan is repayable on the conclusion
				of the agreed tenure. The assessee has booked interest cost to forward
				ICDs to group -concern. This is against the very nature of an ICD.
				The ICD should be out of surplus funds with the company.
			</Para3>
			<page no="730"></page>
			<Para3>
				5. That during the previous assessment proceedings the assessee has
				failed to prove that borrowed money had not been utilised for non-business
				purposes. This is fact on record reference is drawn to previous
				assessment orders of the assessee.
			</Para3>
			<Para3>
				6. That additions were made by the Assessing Officer on account of
				interest claimed under section 36(1)(iii) of the Act.
			</Para3>
			<Para2>
				4.5.4 Without prejudice to the facts mentioned above, this
				is not a case where the debts were written off due to inability
				in recovering the debts, but write off has happened as a result
				of assignment of such debts to the assessee’s group company Ibrox
				Aviation and -Trading P. Ltd. (IATPL) in a single accounting year
				the assessee has assigned the dates to a group company (which is
				not an asset reconstruction company) and has taken a haircut of
				whooping Rs. 251.30 crores in its books of account. The transaction
				with IATPL is -discussed in paragraph 3.7 in detail. Further as
				discussed in the -preceding paragraph in the case of an ICD, the
				amount is repayable on demand whereas the loan is repayable on the
				conclusion of the agreed tenure. Had the assessee had doubts about
				a particular ICD being recovered back, it would have recalled the
				ICD in that year itself.
			</Para2>
			<Para2>
				4.5.5 It is thus clear from the facts mentioned above that
				the assessee in previous year had advanced ICDs to its group concerns
				from the ICDs from group entities and loans taken from financial
				institutions. That such advances made to group concerns have been
				written off during the year not on account of failure to recover
				the debts, but on account of reassignment of such deposits to a
				group concern. Against the reassignment of net deposits worth Rs.
				250 crores, the assessee has received a sum of Rs. 4.8 crores. As
				a result, the assessee has booked a loss of Rs. 251.30 crores. It
				is thus clear that this is not a case of advance turning bad, but
				a sham transaction to book fictitious expenses in the books of account.
			</Para2>
			<Para2>
				4.6 Again, vide submissions dated December 24, 2019 the assessee stated
				that the loss incurred on ICDs and security along with accrued interest
				is allowable as deduction under section 36(1)(vii) read with section
				36(2) and under section 28(i). The submissions of the assessee are
				not acceptable. The conditions in relation to business loss are clear
				:
			</Para2>
			<Para3>
				1. That it should be incidental to the carrying on of the
				business.
			</Para3>
			<page no="731"></page>
			<Para3>2. Should be on revenue account.</Para3>
			<Para3>3. Should be a real loss and not a notional fictitious one.</Para3>
			<Para3>
				4. Should have actually been incurred and not anticipated
				as -certain to occur in future.
			</Para3>
			<Para3>
				5. Should not be prohibited from being deducted under the -provisions
				of the Act.
			</Para3>
			<Para2>
				Hence the loss was not incidental to the business, nor was
				of a -revenue account. It was a future anticipated loss. Clearly
				the loss claimed on ICD is not allowable under section 28(i) of
				the Act.
			</Para2>
			<Para2>
				4.7 Agreement with Ibrox Aviation and Trading P. Ltd. : As -discussed
				above the assessee has booked loss on account of assignment of debts
				to its group concern IATPL. IATPL is an Essar group company and
				is not an asset reconstruction company. In fact, IATPL is a shareholder
				of Essar Oil. Essar Oil has advanced ICDs to VPTL and VOTL the agreement
				to assign certain assets and liabilities of the assessee-company
				to IATPL was executed on March 31, 2017. In the agreement Essar Ports
				and Shipping Ltd., Mauritius has acted as the guarantor.
			</Para2>
			<Para2>
				4.7.2 As per the agreement with VOTL the seller of identified assets
				and liabilities would sell its assets and liabilities to IATPL for
				a consideration of Rs. 4.8 crores. The identified assets total to
				Rs. 955.4 crores. The assets where ICDs advanced by the assessee
				to five -entities that are either subsidiaries or shareholders of
				Essar Oil. The identified liabilities were Rs. 699 crores of ICD
				the assessee owed to Essar Oil Ltd. Thus, net assets of Rs. 256.4
				crores were assigned to IATPL. Against such assignment IATPL paid
				a sum of Rs. 4.8 crores to the assessee. The differential amount
				of Rs. 251.3 crores were booked by the assessee as loss in its books
				of account.
			</Para2>
			<Para2>
				4.7.3 Clearly the entire transaction is an intragroup arrangement, which
				has led to the assessee claiming a loss of Rs. 251.6 crores. The loss
				is a national one and not actual loss. The assessee has brought nothing
				on record to show that efforts were made to recover the ICD before
				assigning the same to a group concern at a steep haircut.
			</Para2>
			<Para2>
				4.8 In the light of the facts brought out in the preceding
				paragraphs, the loss claimed by the assessee of Rs. 251.30 crores
				on account of company’s inability to collect ICD and interest thereon,
				the amount specified is disallowed. Penalty proceedings under section 270A
				of the Income-tax Act are initiated separately for misreporting and
				under-reporting of income.
			</Para2>
			<Para2>(Addition : Rs. 2,51,30,00,000).”</Para2>
		</Quote>
		<page no="732"></page>
		<Para>
			<Bold>16.</Bold> Thus the learned Assessing Officer held that
			it is a sham transaction and loss is fictitious, it is not allowable
			as bad debt and not allowable as business loss.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>17.</Bold> The assessee challenged this addition before
			the learned Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals). In para Nos. 5.1
			to 5.7 the learned -Commissioner of Income-tax has discussed the
			proceedings before the learned Assessing Officer. In paragraph No.
			5.8 onwards the findings of the learned Commissioner of Income-tax
			(Appeals) are rendered as under :
		</Para>
		<Quote>
			<Para2>
				”5.8 At the appellate stage, the appellant has contended
				that loss arising on transfer of ICDs is allowable as a deduction.
				However, if the assessee had doubts about a particular ICD being
				recovered back it would have recalled the ICD in that year itself
				instead of bearing loss arising on transfer. Here the loss was not
				incidental to the business, nor was of revenue account. As pointed
				out by the Assessing Officer, the assessee has booked a loss on
				account of assignment of debts to its group concern IATPL. IATPL
				is Essar group company and is not an asset reconstruction company.
				In the fact, IATPL is a shareholder of Essar Oil. Essar Oil had
				advanced ICDs to VPTL and VOTL and the agreement to assign certain
				assets and liability of the assessee-company to IATPL was executed
				on March 31, 2017. Appellant’s contention that the loss on account
				of company’s inability to collect the amount specified of Rs. 251.30
				crores cannot be entertained since, it has not proven or made any
				efforts to collect the said amount. The appellant has failed to
				prove that how it was unable to collect the amount also brought
				nothing on record to show that efforts were made to recover the
				ICD before assigning the same to a group -concern.
			</Para2>
			<Para2>
				5.9 In this respect, the appellant has relied upon some case
				law. However, they are not relevant in the case of appellant. In
				the case of <Reference>
					<CRTo>
						<Title>
							CIT v. Investa Industrial Corporation
							Ltd.
						</Title>
					</CRTo>
				</Reference><Footnote>3</Footnote> the financial
				position of the company being managed by the assessee deteriorated
				and the company went under liquidation, the assessee wrote of the
				principal and interest outstanding from the company in its books
				of account and claimed the same as a bad debt or business loss.
				Wherein the honourable High Court held if as a result of the managed
				company having gone into liquidation, the advances became irrecoverable,
				the loss would have to be regarded as a trading loss and the same
				would have to be allowed as a deduction while computing the income
				of the<page no="733"></page>assessee. However, in case of appellant the fact is different,
				it has not gone into liquidation and that the advances became irrecoverable.
			</Para2>
			<Para2>
				5.10 The next claim made by the appellant that as per the
				provisions of section 36(2) of the Act, the amount of bad debt which
				is written off as irrecoverable in the accounts of the assessee
				shall be allowed as a deduction in computing business income. The
				basic requirement to allow bad debt is that the amount claimed as
				bad debt should have offered in earlier year as revenue. However,
				the year in which the revenue pertaining to its data was not offered
				with -evidence and the appellant has failed to justify the claim
				of bad debts under section 36(1)(vi) of the Act. In absence of any
				critical evidence before me, I am unable to accept the contention
				of the appellant and held that the loss is a notional one and not
				actual loss.
			</Para2>
			<Para2>
				5.11 Besides, claim is made by the appellant that it has
				been -consistently treating the interest income arising from ICD
				is and the receivables given to its various group companies as profits
				and gains arising from business or profession in its return of income.
				This fact has not been denied by Assessing Officer anywhere in his
				order. The argument made by the appellant cannot absolve it from
				its liability. The Assessing Officer had placed on record the entire
				gamut of finding and there is no further requirement for elaboration.
				In view of the overall facts discussed as above addition made of
				Rs. 2,51,30,00,000 on account of loss on transfer of ICD is apparent.
				This ground of appeal is dismissed.”
			</Para2>
		</Quote>
		<Para>
			<Bold>18.</Bold> Thus the learned Commissioner of Income-tax
			(Appeals) confirmed the disallowance on all three aspects. Therefore, the assessee
			is in appeal before us. Assessee has filed a paper book containing
			628 pages initially and further paper book containing 629 pages
			to 914 pages were submitted on June 19, 2023 as additional evidence. The assessee
			has also submitted in response to query raised by the Bench a paper
			book containing five -different documents to substantiate it claim
			in response to the date of hearing held on February 14, 2024.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>19.</Bold> The learned authorised representative first
			took us to page No. 230 of the paper book to show that as per annexure
			A details of assets and -liabilities assigned under agreement with
			Ibrox Aviation and Trading P. Ltd. are mentioned as five different
			inter-corporate deposits amounting to Rs. 738.25 crores, security
			deposit amounting to Rs. 3 crores along with other receivable or
			advances of Rs. 2.18 crores over and above outstanding interest
			due of Rs. 211.94 crores making the total assets assigned to the Ibrox Aviation
			and Trading P. Ltd. of Rs. 955.38 crores. The assessee has<page no="734"></page>also
			a liability in the name of Essar Oil Ltd. of ICD of Rs. 699.29 crores which
			is also assigned to that company. Thus, it was explained that the total
			assets of Rs. 955.38 crores and a liability of Rs. 699.29 crores
			have been assigned having a net asset value of Rs. 256.09 crores
			for Rs. 4.79 crores and therefore a loss of Rs. 251.30 crores were
			incurred by the assessee on its transaction. Thus, it was stated
			that the claim of the assessee is either to allow the same as bad
			debtor to allow it as business loss.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>20.</Bold> He submitted that the assessee has already
			received the interest out of the outstanding sum amounting to Rs.
			75.84 crores which has been offered by the assessee as income during
			the year or in earlier years and therefore even if the part of the
			income has been offered for taxation in the earlier years, it satisfies
			the condition laid down under section 36(2) of the Act. It is not
			the condition that the whole of the amount which has been written
			off should have been shown as income in the earlier years. Therefore,
			his argument was that when the income has been shown of interest on
			such inter-corporate deposits, even if part and not full, and then
			write off debt of inter-corporate deposit as well as outstanding
			accrued interest as a bad debts is eligible.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>21.</Bold> For this proposition he relied upon the decision
			of honourable -Bombay High Court in the case of <Reference>
				<CRTo>
					<Title>CIT v. Pudumjee Pulp and Paper Mills Ltd.</Title>
				</CRTo>
			</Reference>
			<Footnote>4</Footnote>,
			wherein one part of the debt was offered to tax it was held that
			it will satisfy the claim of deduction of that under section 36(1)(i)
			of the Act. The learned authorised representative specifically referred
			to the question raised before the honourable High Court in paragraph
			No. 2, the facts that part of the bad debt was offered for income-tax
			and then paragraph No. 12 where the honourable High Court allowed
			the bad debts. He further referred to the decision of honourable
			Bombay High Court in the case of <Reference>
				<CRTo>
					<Title>
						CIT v. Shreyas
						S. Morakhia
					</Title>
				</CRTo>
			</Reference><Footnote>5</Footnote>, wherein
			in case of a share broker unrealised value of shares from the clients
			were held to be deductible under section 36(1)(vii) if brokerage
			is taken to the profit and loss account. He further referred to
			the question before the honourable High Court in paragraph No. (1)
			and thereafter reference of Special Bench in paragraph No. (3) and argument
			of the assessee in paragraph No. (4). He thereafter referred to paragraph
			No. 14, wherein it has been held that where the assessee is a stock broker
			on behalf of its client is as much a part of that of shares -transacted
			as is the brokerage which is charged by the assessee on the transaction.
			Therefore, his argument was that the assessee satisfies the conditions
			laid down under the act for write-off of the bad debt.<page no="735"></page>Accordingly,
			the assessee should be granted the same as a deduction as bad debt.
			He further referred to the decision of the honourable Bombay High
			Court in <Reference>
				<CRTo>
					<Title>
						Pr. CIT v. Mahindra Engineering
						and Chemical Products Ltd.
					</Title>
				</CRTo>
			</Reference><Footnote>6</Footnote>,
			dated October 27, 2021, wherein the facts clearly shows that when the
			interest income is brought to tax as business income in the earlier assessment
			years, advances made in the course of the business when return of
			their should be allowed as a deduction under section 36(1)(vii) and
			section 36(2)(i) of the Act. The learned authorised representative -specifically
			referred to paragraph number three of the order wherein based on
			the earlier decisions referred the honourable High Court in paragraph Nos.
			10, 11 and 12 has decided the issue.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>22.</Bold> The learned authorised representative also
			submitted that interest on inter-corporate deposits assigned wherein
			it was submitted that total interest of Rs. 211.95 crores are assigned
			and for the assessment year 2014-15 Rs. 42.74 crores have been offered
			for income-tax, a sum of Rs. 38.81 crores have been offered for
			tax in the assessment year 2015-16, a sum of Rs. 98.68 crores have
			been offered for the assessment year 2016-17 and a sum of Rs. 17.91
			crores have been offered for income-tax. Thus, the assessee fulfils
			the condition under section 36(2) of the Act. Therefore, he submits
			that the write-off of the inter-corporate deposit is eligible for deduction
			as a bad debt.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			23. On February 14, 2024 after hearing the Bench made a following order
			sheet entry :
		</Para>
		<Quote>
			<Para2>
				”The assessee has filed appeal mainly on the issue
				of disallowance of Rs. 251.30 crores and other additions. For this
				loss assessee has sold its and certain advances of Rs. 955 crores
				and liabilities of Rs. 6,99 crores to a related party for a consideration
				of only Rs. 4.8 crores and claimed deduction of Rs. 251 crores.
				The assessment order clearly states that there is no business rational
				of above transaction. On reading of annual report also we found
				that there is a scheme of arrangement and change in holding company,
				in the auditor’s report there is a qualification and management
				reply thereto. As per note No. 56 of annual report, it is evident
				that the above transactions are offshoot of larger understanding
				between Essar Oil Ltd. entering into share purchase agreement. Therefore,
				rational of sale of assets worth Rs. 955 crores included in the
				above when it is realising interest, sold by the assessee along
				with liability of Rs. 6.99 crores for Rs. 4.8 crores only need to
				be examined. The authorised representative is directed to explain
				the same.”
			</Para2>
		</Quote>
		<page no="736"></page>
		<Para>
			<Bold>24.</Bold> In response to the above order sheet enquiry
			from the Bench, the assessee submitted a letter dated May 20, 2024. The learned
			authorised representative invited our attention to press note placed
			at page No. 948-947 of <Italics>Business Today</Italics> wherein
			it was stated that Essar Rosneft Complete deal worth US $ 12.9 billion.
			He further submitted that various news reports placed at page Nos.
			915 to 1026 are publicly available documents which explains the
			rationale of the above deal. He further submitted that on attention
			to page No. 231 is again that the assessee has transferred both the
			assets and liabilities. The inter-corporate deposits were an asset
			having the grave doubt about recovery of the amount. The assessee
			was hopeful if there is a change in shareholding there would be
			improvement in the chances of recovery. He referred to 5 inter-corporate
			deposits which were doubtful of recovery part of the transfer he
			also referred to liability payable of Rs. 699 crores also part of
			the transferred asset. With reference to the rational, he referred
			to paper book page Nos. 1027 to 1044 which is a credit rating for
			bank facilities of Vadinar Oil Terminal Ltd. by care ratings dated May
			23, 2018. He referred to page No. 1030 wherein detailed rational
			of Essar Oil Ltd. was mentioned in that report. He referred to page
			No. 1035 of that care ratings report relating to Vadinar Oil Terminal
			Ltd. He further referred to the financial statement of the assessee
			for the assessment years 2018-19 to 2020-21 to show that there is
			a decline in interest cost, there is decrease in borrowing there
			is increase in gross revenue and corresponding increase in profit
			before taxes. Thus, he submitted that change in shareholders and
			transfer of assets and liabilities is for the benefit of assessee-company
			and that is the justification why the assets and liabilities are transferred
			together. It was further stated that the interest is not realised but
			accrued to the assessee and is outstanding. It was further submitted that
			transfer of these assets is based on the valuation report of grant Thornton
			issued in April 2017 and therefore the transaction made by the assessee
			is for the benefit of the assessee.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>25.</Bold> The learned authorised representative categorically
			submitted that the assessee does not have a share purchase agreement
			and so it is not available and hence not furnished. It stated that
			such share purchase agreement is between Essar group of company
			with the buyer. The -assessee does not have any access to such agreement
			and therefore it is not submitted.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>26.</Bold> Though the learned authorised representative
			did not state in -writing in letter dated May 28, 2024 that the
			assessee does not have a share purchase agreement and therefore
			it is not available and hence it is not<page no="737"></page>submitted. However, it was
			an oral argument of the assessee though the Bench specifically asked
			as per the order sheet.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>27.</Bold> The learned authorised representative further
			referred to the response of the management on the qualification
			in the audit report wherein it is mentioned that after due consideration,
			the company sold the portfolio of outstanding receivables amounting
			to Rs. 2,569.42 crores and payable is amounting to Rs. 2,298.21
			crores from certain related and other entities to Essar Steel Jharkhand
			Ltd. and Ibrox Aviation and Trading P. Ltd., at fair valuation.
			On the basis of fair valuation of these outstanding receivables
			and payables, the company has debited to the profit and loss Rs.
			177.50 crores as an exceptional item, the company expects to realise
			the carrying values of the investment and other deals through the
			escrow arrangement shortly. Therefore, there was a justification
			and rational for the above deal.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>28.</Bold> The learned Commissioner of Income-tax-Departmental
			representative vehemently supported the order of the learned lower
			authorities and stated that it is a sham transaction as stated by
			the learned Assessing Officer confirmed by the learned Commissioner
			of Income-tax (Appeals). The assessee has not submitted the relevant
			document before the lower authorities on this issue. Further the
			clubbing of the assets and liabilities together does not have any
			rational. He further stated that the deduction is neither available
			as bad debt as claimed by the assessee before the learned Assessing
			Officer and not also as a business loss. He further submitted that the
			learned Assessing Officer has given a detail reason which are not -controverted
			by the assessee.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>29.</Bold> The learned Commissioner of Income-tax-Departmental
			representative further submitted that all the decision cited by
			the learned authorised representative are taking the claim that
			the claim of the assessee is under the head bad debt, it is not
			about that but a sham transaction which has been claimed as a deduction
			or business loss by the assessee. He submitted that when the gross
			assets of the value of Rs. 955 crores which are earning good income
			along with the liability of Essar Oil Ltd. of Rs. 699.29 crores having
			the net asset value of Rs. 256.09 crores are sold to a sister concern for
			only Rs. 4.79 crores itself shows that the transaction is sham.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>30.</Bold> He further submitted that there is a qualification
			in the auditor’s report wherein there is a qualified opinion is
			given by the auditor. He -further referred to the profit and loss
			account of the assessee wherein as per note No. 40 a sum of Rs.
			918.68 crores have been written off. He -further referred to note
			No. 40 wherein a sum of Rs. 177.50 crores have been debited to the
			profit and loss account as specified in note No. 56. He<page no="738"></page>also took
			us to note No. 56, wherein there is an offshoot of the transaction of
			sale of major shareholders of the Essar Oil Ltd. selling the stake
			to the third parties and thereafter several agreements entered wherein
			this sum is mentioned. The assessee has failed to produce despite
			the Bench asking for the same agreement. He further stated that
			if the assessee is not aware or not in possession of that agreement
			how it can refer to in the annual accounts of the assessee and then
			make a reference of the provision of investment. He further referred
			to note No. 16 and note No. 21 which are also interlinked. Therefore,
			his argument was that the assessee is hiding behind the original
			agreement entered by the majority shareholders of Essar Oil Ltd.
			with third-party. He therefore submitted that the claim of the assessee
			is neither bona fide, nor allowable under the provisions of the law
			and is based on hidden facts.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>31.</Bold> We have carefully considered the rival contention
			and perused the orders of the learned lower authorities. Short issue
			involved in this appeal is that when the assessee has transferred
			its certain financial assets along with certain financial liabilities
			for a consideration to a sister concern, loss arising thereon whether
			should be considered as bad debt, deductible as a business loss
			or it is not at all allowable to the assessee.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>32.</Bold> The facts succinctly stated shows that the assessee
			has transferred certain inter corporate deposits with its group
			companies (Essar group) and certain inter corporate liabilities
			in the same group and has incurred a loss. The assessee has transferred
			following inter corporate deposits/advances/interest accrued thereon :
			<Table>
				<TBody>
					<Row>
						<Entry>
							<Para>
								Sl.
								No.
							</Para>
						</Entry>
						<Entry>
							<Para>Name of the company</Para>
						</Entry>
						<Entry>
							<Para>
								Total amount
								(Rs. in crores)
							</Para>
						</Entry>
					</Row>
					<Row>
						<Entry>
							<Para>1.</Para>
						</Entry>
						<Entry>
							<Para>Essar Bulk Terminal Ltd.</Para>
						</Entry>
						<Entry>
							<Para>145.60</Para>
						</Entry>
					</Row>
					<Row>
						<Entry>
							<Para>2.</Para>
						</Entry>
						<Entry>
							<Para>
								Imperial Consultants
								and Securities
							</Para>
						</Entry>
						<Entry>
							<Para>306.87</Para>
						</Entry>
					</Row>
					<Row>
						<Entry>
							<Para>3.</Para>
						</Entry>
						<Entry>
							<Para>
								Essar Steel India
								Ltd.
							</Para>
						</Entry>
						<Entry>
							<Para>305.53</Para>
						</Entry>
					</Row>
					<Row>
						<Entry>
							<Para>4.</Para>
						</Entry>
						<Entry>
							<Para>Essar Shipping Ltd.</Para>
						</Entry>
						<Entry>
							<Para>54.95</Para>
						</Entry>
					</Row>
					<Row>
						<Entry>
							<Para>5.</Para>
						</Entry>
						<Entry>
							<Para>Essar Bulk Terminal Paradip Ltd.</Para>
						</Entry>
						<Entry>
							<Para>142.53</Para>
						</Entry>
					</Row>
					<Row>
						<Entry/>
						<Entry>
							<Para>Total</Para>
						</Entry>
						<Entry>
							<Para>955.38</Para>
						</Entry>
					</Row>
				</TBody>
			</Table>
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>33.</Bold> The assessee has also transferred the liability
			of following loan :
		</Para>
		<Para>Essar Oil Ltd. 	Rs. 699.29 crores</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>34.</Bold> Thus, the net asset value of the assets transferred
			is Rs. 256.09 crores. The issue is that it is sold to a sister concern
			IATPL only for Rs. 4.98 crores. Thus, the assessee has incurred
			loss of Rs. 251.30 crores. Whether these losses allowable as bad
			debt, business loss or not.
		</Para>
		<page no="739"></page>
		<Para>
			<Bold>35.</Bold> To reach at the conclusion, following important
			fact noted from the annual report of the assessee-company are required
			to be mentioned. There is a scheme of arrangement and change in
			holding company as per directors’ report at page No. 13 of the annual
			report of the company wherein it is mentioned as under :
		</Para>
		<Quote>
			<Para2>”Scheme of arrangement and change in holding company.</Para2>
			<Para2>
				As on March 31, 2016, Essar Ports Ltd. (EPL) was the holding -company
				of the company. In view of the composite scheme of arrangement amongst
				the company, Vadinar Ports and Terminals Ltd., Essar Power and Minerals
				Ltd., Yash Hotels P. Ltd., Hazira Coke Ltd. and Essar Ports Ltd.
				(the scheme) as approved by the honourable High Court of Gujarat
				effective July 1, 2016, Essar Power and -Minerals Ltd. (EPML) and
				Vadinar Ports Terminals Ltd. have merged with your company.
			</Para2>
			<Para2>
				As a result, your company has issued equity shares to all
				the shareholders of EPML as on the record date fixed for the same.
				The shares held by EPL in your company have been cancelled as a
				consequence of the scheme.
			</Para2>
			<Para2>
				In view of the above, upon the implementation of the scheme Essar
				Ports and Shipping Ltd .(EPSL), Mauritius became the holding company
				of your company.
			</Para2>
			<Para2>
				The shares held by EPSL were acquired by Essar Steel Jharkhand Ltd.
				(ESJL) and as a consequence ESJL became the holding company of your
				company effective March 31, 2017.
			</Para2>
			<Para2>
				Thereafter, Essar Oil Ltd. has acquired the entire shareholding
				held by ESJL constituting 97.63 per cent. of share capital of your
				company as on the date is the holding company.”
			</Para2>
		</Quote>
		<Para>
			<Bold>36.</Bold> On examination of the annual report of company,
			the profit and loss account show an exceptional item debited of
			Rs. 918.68 crores details of which is available in note No. 40.
			Note No. 40 details of the exceptional item shows that :
		</Para>
		<Para2>
			(a) Debit to profit and loss on reassessment of the company’s
			ability to collect the amount specified in note No. 56 Rs. 177.50
			crores.
		</Para2>
		<Para>
			<Bold>37.</Bold> As there is reference of note of 56 that
			note speaks as under :
		</Para>
		<Quote>
			<Para2>
				”56. As reported in the earlier year, majority stake
				in the company was to be acquired by Essar Oil Ltd. (EOL) as a condition
				precedent to the arrangements (SPAs) entered into by the majority
				shareholders of EOL to sell their stake to third parties, and in
				escrow arrangement was to be put in place to apply the sale consideration,
				to the extent<page no="740"></page>required, towards discharge of amounts due to the
				company from certain related parties. The majority stake in the
				company has since been acquired by EOL. However, the closure of
				sale of the stake in EOL is taking longer than previously envisaged.
				The company in the interim continued to transact with the related
				parties and has -reassessed its ability to realise the dues from
				related parties (including investment in a subsidiary company pursuant
				to acceptance of offer to buy-back the shares from the subsidiary).
				Through the said escrow arrangement, based on which it has debited
				to the statement of profit and loss Rs. 177.50 crores as an exceptional
				item. The carrying values of the investment and other dues to be
				realised through the escrow arrangement aggregate on March 31, 2017,
				to Rs. 3,613.44 crores (comprises investment in equity shares of
				enneagon of Rs. 3,033.21 crores refer note No. 16, and other receivables
				of Rs. 580.23 crore-refer note No. 21).”
			</Para2>
		</Quote>
		<Para>
			<Bold>38.</Bold> Note No. 57 on going concern is also required
			to be considered which is as under :
		</Para>
		<Quote>
			<Para2>
				”57. <Italics>Going concern</Italics>
			</Para2>
			<Para2>
				The ability of the company to continue as a going concern
				is predicated on the successful implementation of SPAs together
				with the escrow arrangement for deployment of the sales consideration towards
				the liquidation of amounts due to the company from certain related
				parties and have the required cash flows to meet its financial obligations.”
			</Para2>
		</Quote>
		<Para>
			<Bold>39.</Bold> It is interesting to note that the assessee
			has entered into an agreement for transfer of identified assets
			and liabilities between Vadinar Oil Terminal Ltd. and Essar Steel
			Jharkhand Ltd. on March 31, 2017 wherein details of the third parties
			are identified assets amounting to Rs. 1,614 crores along with the
			amount of identified liability of Rs. 1,599 crores -having net value
			of Rs. 15.14 crores were sold for net consideration of Rs. 15.1
			crores. Therefore, in sale of assets and liabilities to Essar Steel Jharkhand
			Ltd. there is no loss or profit.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>40.</Bold> The transaction with Ibrox Aviation and Trading
			P. Ltd. of Rs. 4.78 crores are described in the related party transaction
			in note No. 58 to the annual accounts wherein it is stated that
			inter-corporate deposits taken being liability of Rs. 699.29 crores
			and the assets having a value of Rs. 955.37 crores have been transferred
			to that company for Rs. 4.78 crores whose net asset value is Rs.
			256.14 crores.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>41.</Bold> On the same date (along with the sale of
			similar assets to Essar Steel Jharkhand Ltd.) on March 31, 2017
			and agreement for transfer of identified<page no="741"></page>assets and liabilities
			was entered into between the assessee and Ibrox -Aviation and Trading
			P. Ltd., wherein assets to the tune of Rs. 955.4 crores and a liability
			of Rs. 699 crores were transferred to that company for a -consideration
			of Rs. 4.8 crores having a net asset value of Rs. 256.40 crores.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>42.</Bold> The liability in both the cases were pertaining
			to Essar Oil Ltd. Rs. 1,599 crores were transferred to Essar Steel
			Jharkhand Ltd. and Rs. 699 crores were transferred to Ibrox Aviation
			and Trading P. Ltd.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>43.</Bold> This is also to be noted that that in transaction
			with Essar Steel Jharkhand Ltd., no profit or loss was incurred
			on transfer of the group inter corporate deposits and liability
			of Essar Oil Ltd. However, in case of the assessee in transaction
			with Ibrox Aviation and Trading P. Ltd. the assessee has incurred
			loss of Rs. 251.30 crores. Out of these Rs. 251.30 crores the assessee
			has reduced Rs. 73.80 crores being the expected credit loss resulting into
			net tax charged to exceptional item of Rs. 177.50 crores.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>44.</Bold> It is also interesting that auditors have
			given a qualified opinion as per audit report dated August 14, 2017.
			The basis for qualified opinion as per page No. 33 of the annual
			report is as under :
		</Para>
		<Quote>
			<Para2>
				”<Italics>Basis for qualified opinion</Italics>
			</Para2>
			<Para2>
				Attention is invited to note No. 56 regarding the ability
				of the company to realise investment in a subsidiary company and
				amounts due from certain related parties, which is predicated on
				successful closure of the sale of shares by the majority shareholders
				of Essar Oil Ltd., The holding company and application of the sales
				consideration towards the discharge of the aforesaid amounts, as
				explained in the note. In view of the delay in achieving closure
				of the sale transaction and the consequent collection of the amounts
				as envisaged, and -further the reassessment by the company of its
				ability to realise the entire investment and other dues through
				the escrow arrangement, we are unable to express an opinion on the
				recover ability of the -caring values of the investment and the
				dues aggregating to Rs. 3,613.44 crores as of March 31, 2017 or
				debit to the statement of profit and loss of Rs. 177.50 crores for
				the year.”
			</Para2>
		</Quote>
		<Para>
			<Bold>45.</Bold> Thus, there is no qualification with respect
			to transaction of sale of similar assets and liabilities to Essar
			Steel Jharkhand Ltd., but it is on transaction of Ibrox Aviation
			and Trading P. Ltd. only.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>46.</Bold> Now it is interesting to note that the management
			in its reply in the director’s report to the qualification of the
			auditor as under :
		</Para>
		<page no="742"></page>
		<Para2>
			(a) Management response to qualification under basis for
			qualified opinion in the auditor’s report on standalone and consolidated
			financial statements :
		</Para2>
		<Quote>
			<Para2>
				“The company had receivable from various group companies
				and other entities, operating in steel, shipping, and other sectors.
				Due to the weakening of the sectors and data duration of the financial -condition
				(including restructuring of that is) of these entities, a situation
				has arise in wherein the value of the receivables from these entities
				has significantly declined and recovery of their dues is likely to
				take a substantial amount of time. The company, therefore, we, after
				considering the report of an independent third-party, its ability to
				collect the outstanding balances.
			</Para2>
			<Para2>
				Further, as reported in the earlier year, controlling stake
				being non-public shareholding in the company was to be acquired
				by Essar Oil Ltd. (EOL) as a condition precedent to the share purchase
				agreements (SPA) executed on October 15, 2016 by the majority stakeholders
				of EOL to sell their shareholding to Petrol Complex Pte Ltd. and
				Kesani Enterprises Co. Ltd. As a result, the company will no longer
				remain a part of the Essar group and accordingly the company intends
				to settle all its assets and liabilities and realise the dues from related
				parties and other entities as envisaged in the transaction -documents
				exist to pursuant to the SPAs.
			</Para2>
			<Para2>
				After due consideration, the company sold the portfolio of
				outstanding receivables amounting to Rs. 2,569.42 crores and payable amounting
				to Rs. 2,298.21 crores from certain related parties and other entities
				to Essar Steels Jharkhand Ltd. and Ibrox Aviation and Trading P.
				Ltd., at fair valuation. On the basis of fair valuation of these
				outstanding receivables and payables, the company has debited to
				profit and loss Rs. 177.50 crores as an exceptional item. The -company
				expects to realise the caring values of the investment and other
				dues through the escrow arrangement shortly.”
			</Para2>
		</Quote>
		<Para>
			<Bold>47.</Bold> Thus, it is apparent that in the case of
			transaction with Essar Steel Jharkhand Ltd. where the outstanding
			receivable of sixteen parties amounting to Rs. 1,614.14 crores were
			transferred, there is no decrease in fair market value of a single
			rupee. Whereas on receivables transferred to Ibrox Aviation and Trading
			P. Ltd. on transfer of receivables of Rs. 955.38 crores the loss
			of Rs. 251.30 crores were recorded.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>48.</Bold> In both the cases the liability transferred
			was with respect to Essar Oil Ltd. In the case of Essar Steel Jharkhand
			Ltd. the liability of EOL of Rs. 1,599 crores were transferred whereas
			in case of Ibrox Aviation and<page no="743"></page>Trading P. Ltd. the liability of Rs.
			699.29 crores were transferred. It is to be noted that Essar Oil
			Ltd. is the ultimate holding company of the assessee in view of
			the change in the structure and management of shareholding of the
			company.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>49.</Bold> We find that the assessee has produced the
			report of Grant Thorton in April 2017 on recoverable values of receivables
			from Essar Shipping Ltd. in terms of the report dated April 4, 2017.
			On the report on recoverable values of receivable from Essar Shipping
			Ltd. and Imperial Consultants and Securities, it was held that out
			of the ICD including interest under the receivable of Essar Shipping
			Ltd. of Rs. 55 crores the range of the recovery of the receivable
			is only 93 per cent. to 99.4 per cent. and in the case of Imperial Consultant
			and Securities Ltd. on ICD and interest another receivable of Rs.
			306.9 crores the range of the receivable is only 44.6 per cent.
			to 59 per cent. Similarly report on recoverable value of Essar Steel India
			Ltd. as per report dated April 4, 2017, on outstanding of Rs. 305 crores,
			it is stated that the interest of Rs. 80 crores are not recoverable
			and on the balance sum of Rs. 224 crores the recovery would be in
			the range of 5 per cent. to 14 per cent. Thus, out of the total
			receivable of Rs. 955.38 crores, the recoverable report of only
			Rs. 667.35 crores were placed before us, thus for the balance Rs.
			328 crores there is no reply about the recover ability report.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>50.</Bold> All the reports of the Grant Thornton are
			pertaining to the period April 2017 and were dated April 4, 2017
			whereas the agreement with the Ibrox Aviation and Trading P. Ltd.
			was entered into on March 31, 2017. Therefore, the consideration
			value of Rs. 4.8 crores were decided earlier without having the
			recover ability report of Grant Thorton Ltd. Therefore, in case
			of sale of receivable to Essar Steel Jharkhand Ltd. nor losses incurred
			but in case of transaction with Ibrox Aviation and Trading P. Ltd. loss
			of Rs. 251 crores were incurred. Thus, there is no justification
			of transfer of assets of 955.38 crores and the liability of Rs. 699.29
			crores having a net asset value of Rs. 256.09 crores to a sister
			concern for a meagre -consideration of Rs. 4.79 crores.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>51.</Bold> The assessee also submitted a resolution
			passed by the circulation on January 18, 2017, placed at page No.
			912 of the paper book wherein it is resolved as under :
		</Para>
		<Quote>
			<Para2>
				”Resolved that in accordance with the provisions of
				the Companies Act, 2013 (Act) read with rule frame thereunder, as
				may be amended from time-to-time and memorandum and articles of
				association of the company, and subject to all other applicable
				laws, the board hereby approves assignment of all the receivables
				from domestic<page no="744"></page>group companies to move the company had extended into
				corporate deposits from time-to-time and simultaneous assignment
				of related payables to Essar Oil Ltd. and the execution of the deed
				of assignment/assignment agreement proposed to be entered into by
				the -company with the relevant group companies.”
			</Para2>
		</Quote>
		<Para>
			<Bold>52.</Bold> We find that in the resolution there is no
			reference of any loss incurred on transfer of the asset, valuation
			of inter corporate deposits at fair market value, to who these assets
			are to be sold, which assets are to be sold to which entity, and
			whether the draft agreement has been perused by the board before
			entering into. Further it is apparent that the agreement of transfer
			of receivable entered by the assessee with Ibrox Aviation and -Terminals
			P. Ltd., produced before us is an unsigned document. Therefore, the
			production of this board resolution which has not discussed any rational
			of selling of inter corporate deposits given at substantial discount, does
			not help the case of the assessee.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>53.</Bold> Though the directors report refers to (page
			No. 15 of annual report) where there is a reply to the qualification
			in the auditor’s report it is -mentioned that :
		</Para>
		<Quote>
			<Para2>
				”Further, as reported in the earlier year, controlling
				stake being non-public shareholding in the company was to be acquired
				by Essar Oil Ltd. (EOL) as a condition precedent to the share purchase -agreements
				(SPA) executed on October 15, 2016 by the majority stakeholders
				of EOL to sell their shareholding to Petrol Complex Pte Ltd. and
				Kesani Enterprises Co. Ltd. As a result, the company will no longer
				remain a part of the Essar group and accordingly the company intends
				to settle all its assets and liabilities and realise the dues from related
				parties and other entities as envisaged in the transaction -documents
				exist to pursuant to the SPAs.”
			</Para2>
		</Quote>
		<Para>
			<Bold>54.</Bold> However, when the Bench asked for these documents
			because that is the offshoot of the transaction by which a sum of
			Rs. 251 crores have been booked in the profit and loss account as
			an exceptional item, it was stated that such agreement is not accessible
			by the assessee and therefore not in a possession of the assessee
			and hence not produced.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>55.</Bold> We note that when the assessee mentions the
			same in its directors’ report, notes on accounts, etc., when the
			going concern itself hinges on that agreement, how the assessee
			is not having any access to that document. The non-production of
			such document goes against the assessee because for proving the
			genuineness of the transaction, onus lies on the assessee. Merely
			relying on the press notes and newspapers items without<page no="745"></page>looking
			at the agreement to which the assessee is privy as it mentions its impact
			on its accounts, etc., does not held the case of the assessee.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>56.</Bold> When the assessee has not produced such agreement
			which is called for by the Bench, auditors of the company have qualified
			the report on this issue itself (write off exceptional item of Rs.
			177.5 crores), going concern of the assessee itself depends on such
			agreement, and fact mentioned above, we do not find any reason to
			deviate from the orders of the learned lower authorities.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>57.</Bold> Regarding the claim of the assessee that the assessee
			should be allowed the deduction as bad debts written off under section
			36(1)(vii) of the Act, we do not find that there is a write off
			of any irrecoverable amount in this case. The assessee has incurred
			loss on sale/transfer of certain -payables and receivables. Therefore,
			the loss cannot be claimed as bad debt. All the arguments of the
			assessee that the assessee has fulfilled the provisions of section
			36(2) of the Act as it has taken into account while computing the
			profit for earlier years by including the interest income as income
			are not relevant. Therefore, the learned lower authorities have -correctly
			held that the assessee is not entitled to claim the deduction of
			bad debt written off in the books of account under section 36(1)(vii)
			of the Act as there is no write off of bad debt.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>58.</Bold> Coming to the alternative claim of the assessee
			of the above sum as trading loss, the learned Assessing Officer
			has categorically held in paragraph No. 4.6 of the assessment order
			that such loss was not incidental to the business and nor was on
			account of revenue it was a future anticipated loss and therefore
			it was disallowed under section 28(i) of the Act. The learned Commissioner
			of Income-tax (Appeals) has confirmed the finding of the learned
			Assessing Officer, we find that the assessee has sold its -payable
			and receivable. On careful reading of the balance-sheet of the assessee-company,
			these are shown as loans and advances. Further the amount of loss
			incurred is also shown as an exceptional item and further in the
			cash flow statement it is shown from the cash flow from investing activities
			and not from operating activities. Therefore, it is apparent that
			it is not the business of the assessee to make investment in inter
			corporate deposits. Therefore, the loss of Rs. 177.50 crores are
			not allowable as a business loss.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>59.</Bold> The argument of the assessee is that it has
			offered the interest income as business income and therefore this
			investment should also be considered as business activity of the
			assessee. We do not find any force in this argument for the simple
			reason that the investments held by the assessee as investment activities.
			Further the memorandum of association<page no="746"></page>of the company furnished before
			us as additional evidence shows that the main object of the assessee-company
			is of shipping and transportation. The serial No. 14 under the head
			object incidental or ancillary to the attainment of the main object
			where lending is mentioned does not help the case of the assessee
			because it is not the business activity of the assessee. It only supports
			the main object of the assessee. Thus, the loss incurred by the assessee
			is on capital account and not on revenue account and it is not a business
			loss which can be granted as deduction to the assessee.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>60.</Bold> Therefore, we do not find any infirmity in
			the order of the learned Assessing Officer in denying the deduction
			of the loss of Rs. 177.5 crores holding that the transaction is
			sham transaction to book fictitious loss in the books of account,
			not allowable as deduction as a bad debt and as a business loss
			which is also confirmed by the learned Commissioner of Income-tax
			(Appeals).
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>61.</Bold> Accordingly ground No. 1 of the appeal of
			the assessee is dismissed.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>62.</Bold> Ground No. 2 of the appeal is with respect
			to the disallowance of interest expenses claimed of Rs. 1,58,12,00,000.
			The fact shows that during the year under consideration the assessee
			has incurred interest expenses to the tune of Rs. 1,009.57 crores
			and has received Rs. 142 crores as interest income. The assessee
			has received inter corporate deposit and security deposits from
			related parties on which interest expenses have been incurred of
			Rs. 395.04 crores which has been debited as interest cost to related
			entities of Rs. 253.50 crores are on account of interest payment
			of intra corporate deposits taken from Essar Oil Ltd. and Rs. 141.50
			crores on account of security deposit given by Essar Oil Ltd. The
			learned Assessing Officer noted that the interest income and expenses
			on inter corporate deposit is considered then the assessee has paid
			interest on inter corporate deposit of Rs. 253.50 crores and received
			an interest of Rs. 95.38 crores. These inter corporate deposits
			are taken from group entities and advances are also given to the
			group entities. The assessee was questioned by the learned Assessing
			Officer which was replied by the assessee on December 17, 2019 stating
			that the inter corporate deposits have been advanced -during the
			business however no interest has been charged on certain inter corporate
			deposits during the year. The assessee relied on the decision of the
			honourable Supreme Court in case of <Reference>
				<CRTo>
					<Title>Hero Cycle</Title>
				</CRTo>
			</Reference> stating
			that there is a commercial expediency for advancing the inter corporate
			deposits. The learned Assessing Officer noted that these inter corporate
			deposits are from and to the group entry entities and no business
			expediency has been established by the assessee that warrants allowability
			of claim of excess interest expenditure on such inter corporate
			deposits more so as a business<page no="747"></page>expenditure. He relied upon the decision
			of the honourable Madras High Court <Reference>
				<CRTo>
					<Title>
						Mir
						Mohd. Ali v. CIT
					</Title>
				</CRTo>
			</Reference><Footnote>7</Footnote>, wherein
			it is held that it is for the assessee to prove that each of the
			loans on which he paid the interest was utilised for the purposes
			of his business. This decision has been affirmed by the -honourable
			High Court in 52 ITR 165. Therefore, the interest income on inter
			corporate deposit was considered by the Assessing Officer under
			the head “Income from other sources” instead of business income
			for statistical purposes and further the excess claim of interest
			amounting to Rs. 158.12 crores (being Rs. 253.30 crores minus Rs.
			95.38 crores) were disallowed. Accordingly, the disallowance of
			Rs. 1,58,12,00,000 was made by the learned Assessing Officer.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>63.</Bold> The assessee challenged the same before the
			learned Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals), wherein the learned
			Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals) has confirmed the addition
			for the reason that when the assessee has raised the business loans
			for the business purposes on which interest liability is incurred
			for payment and on the other hand the funds were advanced to sister
			concern for non-business purposes on interest-free or on average
			interest basis, then the interest payable by the assessee to the financial
			institutions cannot be held to be used funds for business purposes and
			no deduction accordingly can be permitted under section 36(1)(iii)
			of the Act. The learned Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals) has
			also held that the assessee has casually claimed that the said funds
			are used for the business purpose but has not established by the
			appellant during the assessment proceedings or before the appellate
			proceedings. He further held that the contention of the assessee
			that the interest during the year is lower due to the waiver of
			interest from two financially stressed entities is contradicting
			the fact that inter corporate deposits were granted with a view
			to earn interest income and margin in the entire process. Before
			the learned Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals), no details were
			submitted to counter the clear-cut findings of the learned Assessing
			Officer that there was absence of necessary evidence to show that
			the amount borrowed was used for the purpose of the business despite
			adverse comments by the Assessing Officer. It was further held that
			the assessee has not submitted any details in respect of loans availed of and
			loans issued and thus failed to establish the genuineness of the
			transaction. In absence of any new credible evidence placed before
			him, he held that the onus of proving that the borrowed money has
			not been utilised for no business purposes was on the assessee which
			has not been discharged. On the issue of commercial expediency,
			it was stated that the assessee has failed to show any commercial<page no="748"></page>expediency
			and therefore the view of the learned Assessing Officer is -correct.
			Accordingly, he confirmed the disallowance.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>64.</Bold> The learned authorised representative specifically
			referred to the assessment order where the disallowances made. He
			referred to page No. 277 of the paper book which is a summary of
			inter corporate deposits for the financial year 2016-17. He further
			stated that there are two parties, namely, Essar Steel India Ltd.
			and Essar Ltd. to whom the inter corporate deposit is given but
			no interest is charged. It was stated that looking to the position
			of the debtor-assessee was not able to charge any interest thereon. He
			referred to page Nos. 191-192 of the paper book wherein as per -paragraph
			No. (B) the interest on loans and advances to group companies was
			explained. It was stated that company has given an inter corporate deposit
			to group concern during the business. The source of this inter -corporate
			deposits was mixed, i. e., out of internal accruals and out of the inter
			corporate deposits received. As may be seen from the financial statement,
			it has in all cases charged interest on inter corporate deposits granted.
			However, the interest has also been charged at rates higher than the
			rates at which the source of funds has been borrowed. During the
			year, the assessee would not charge any interest on loan given to
			Essar Steel India Ltd. and Essar Dredging Ltd., because of their
			financial and operational challenges and the strong likelihood of
			not receiving those interest. The management of the company in larger
			interest of recovery of inter -corporate deposits decided not to
			charge the interest for this year as is -evident from the financial
			statement. Then he relied extensively on the submission made by
			the assessee at page No. 1934 of paper book. The learned authorised
			representative further referred to the paper book page No. 307 (page
			Nos. 314-315).
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>65.</Bold> The learned authorised representative vehemently
			submitted that identical issue arose in case of the assessee for
			the assessment year in <Reference>
				<CRTo>
					<Title>
						Nayara Energy Ltd. v. Asst.
						CIT
					</Title>
					<Citothers>I. T. A. No. 777/Mum/2022</Citothers>
				</CRTo>
			</Reference> for
			assessment year 2016-17, wherein the co-ordinate Bench vide order
			dated October 10, 2022 has dealt with the same issue and the claim
			of the assessee was allowed.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>66.</Bold> The learned authorised representative further
			referred to <Reference>
				<CRTo>
					<Title>
						Nayara Energy Ltd. v. Asst.
						CIT
					</Title>
				</CRTo>
			</Reference>, M. A. No. 332/Mum/2022 in I. T.
			A. No. 777/Mum/2022 for assessment year 2016-17 decided on February
			6, 2023, wherein as per paragraph No. 2 the issue of inter corporate
			deposits and interest disallowance was raised and he further referred
			to paragraph -number eight of that decision to show that now the
			issue is squarely decided in favour of the assessee. He submits
			that though in the assessment<page no="749"></page>year 2016-17 the issue on different
			context but the interest was granted as deduction. Therefore, the
			issue is covered in favour of the assessee.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>67.</Bold> The learned authorised representative specifically
			referred that it is not the case of the learned Assessing Officer
			that the assessee should have earned interest on ICDs of Essar Oil
			Ltd. and Essar Dredging Ltd. In earlier years, those inter corporate
			deposits were carrying on interest. He referred to the decision
			of the honourable Supreme Court <Reference>
				<CRTo>
					<Title>Veecumsees v. CIT</Title>
				</CRTo>
			</Reference>
			<Footnote>8</Footnote>, wherein paragraph number seven
			in stating that interest year has been -disallowed because of the
			financial position of the debtor but the amount was borrowed for
			the purposes of the business.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>68.</Bold> The learned departmental representative vehemently
			supported the order of the learned lower authorities.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>69.</Bold> We have carefully considered the rival contention
			and perused the orders of the lower authorities. The issue is of
			about the disallowance of the interest expenditure on ICD of Rs.
			1,58,12,00,000. The fact shows that the assessee has incurred interest
			expenditure to the tune of Rs. 1,009.57 crores and has received
			interest of Rs. 142 crores as interest income. On ICD with related
			parties interest expenditure of Rs. 395.04 crores were paid, and
			interest received was of Rs. 253.50 crores from Essar Oil and Rs. 141.54
			crores of security deposit against which the assessee has received
			interest of only Rs. 95.38 crores. It is also a fact admitted that though
			in the corporate deposits have been advanced in the course of the business
			however no interest has been charged on certain deposits during the
			year the reason being advanced by the assessee is of “commercial
			expediency”. During the course of appellate proceedings, the learned
			Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals) has categorically noted that
			whether the funds borrowed was used for the business purposes, no
			details were -furnished by the assessee. Page No. 277 of the paper
			book filed by the assessee clearly shows that as on the end of March
			31, 2016 total -outstanding inter corporate deposits were Rs. 2,57,177
			lakhs. The deposits with Essar Steel Ltd. at the beginning of the
			year was Rs. 30,552.62 lakhs and from Essar Dredging Ltd. of Rs.
			1,23,502.78 lakhs. On both these accounts, the assessee has not
			charged any interest. These ICD is assigned on the last day of the
			financial year and therefore are not outstanding at the end of the
			year. The only reason advanced by the assessee is that the financial
			condition of the debtor was not good and therefore the assessee did
			not charge any interest on these deposits. Except submissions made before
			the lower authorities, no evidence of commercial expediency was submitted
			before us. However, the decision of the co-ordinate Bench in<page no="750"></page>
			<Reference>
				<CRTo>
					<Title>Nayara Energy Ltd. v. Asst. CIT</Title>
					<Citothers>I. T. A. No. 777/Mum/2022</Citothers>
				</CRTo>
			</Reference> for
			the assessment year 2016-17, dated October 10, 2022 was placed before
			us and stated that the decision also deals with the issue para No.
			2 specifically mentioned and subsequently paragraph Nos. 12-13 was
			mentioned. -Subsequently the <Reference>
				<CRTo>
					<Title>
						Nayara Energy
						Ltd. v. Asst. CIT
					</Title>
				</CRTo>
			</Reference>, M. A. No. 332/Mum/2022
			in I. T. A. No. 777/Mum/2022 for assessment year 2016-17 decided
			on February 6, 2023 was discussed. The miscellaneous application
			was only with respect to the restoration of the appeal to the Assessing
			Officer on that issue in I. T. A. No. which was then decided by
			the co-ordinate Bench and deleted the interest disallowance. However,
			the learned authorised representative himself submitted that the
			whole issue is on different -context. It is not the case that the assessee
			has huge non-interest bearing surplus/own funds then the amount
			advanced to the sister concern on which no interest is charged.
			As on March 31, 2017 the total equity of the assessee is only Rs.
			67.08 crores. We have also carefully looked that the page No. 192
			of the paper book wherein a letter dated December 17, 2019 is placed
			before the learned Assessing Officer. On careful perusal of the above
			letter, it was simply statement of judicial principles without any -substantive
			factual details filed before the Assessing Officer or the lower authorities.
			It is also to be seen that the during this year the interest charged
			by the assessee is Rs. 9.472.53 crores whereas the interest repaid
			is also a negative figure (page No. 277 of the paper book). It is
			also to be seen that the outstanding inter corporate deposit of
			Essar Steel India Ltd. was Rs. 22,478 lakhs on which outstanding
			interest was Rs. 80.74 lakhs and in the case of another company
			the outstanding inter corporate deposit was Rs. 1,19,335 lakhs and
			the outstanding interest was of Rs. 4,207 lakhs. Thus, the assessee
			has not used borrowed funds for the purposes of the business but
			has advanced the same to the sister concern without charging any
			interest. In view of this we do not find any infirmity in the order
			of the learned lower authorities in disallowing interest expenditure
			of Rs. 158.12 crores under section 36(1)(iii) of the Act. In the
			result ground Nos. 3-5 of the appeal are dismissed.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>70.</Bold> Ground Nos. 6-7 is with respect to the disallowance
			of interest expenses incurred for the loan used for investment in
			Ennegaon Ltd., -Mauritius.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>71.</Bold> The brief facts of the case shows that during
			the year the assessee has made investment of Rs. 3,033.21 crores
			in the above company. Note No. 56 to the annual account also refers
			of the above investment. The assessee was asked to produce various
			details with respect to the above company. The assessee submitted
			that investment of Rs. 3,033.21 crores<page no="751"></page>were made in three trenches
			on June 29, 2019, September 29, 2016 and December 29, 2016. The
			allotment of the shares took place on September 30, 2016 and February
			23, 2017. This subsidiary company was incorporated into 2015 and
			did not have any business activities before such investment was
			made. It was the claim of the assessee that the above investment
			was meant to carry out trading activity, however, no such activities
			could be carried out because of the prevalent market conditions.
			In August 2017, these shares of the subsidiary company were brought
			back from the assessee. Therefore, in this entire process of less
			than one year the assessee incurred a loss of Rs. 127.93 crores
			on the transaction. The Assessing Officer further noted that over
			and above the above loss, the assessee has also debited finance
			cost of Rs. 171.57 crores in its books of account as -specific finance
			cost incurred towards investment in a subsidiary. Before the Assessing
			Officer no documents in relation to the above proposed plan of acquisition
			of the subsidiary company for the purpose of trading was produced
			and further the record suggested that no business happened in that
			company. Therefore, the learned Assessing Officer reached at a -conclusion
			that the assessee has provided that finance, fund movement shows
			that once the funds landed in its books, there is nothing brought
			on record to prove that this investment was in relation to the business. Accordingly,
			he disallowed the sum of Rs. 171,57,00,000 of the interest expenditure.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>72.</Bold> When the issue was challenged before the
			learned Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals) the assessee submitted
			an explanation for commercial expediency along with the relevant
			judicial precedents for allowability of expenses in the hands of
			the holding company. The assessee submitted that though the intended
			activity of trading did not fructify however the subsidiary had
			paid amount equivalent to the equity investment to a potential supplier
			of motor spirit during the year. The amounts transferred were unsecured
			and carried interest of 5 per cent. per annum up to the date of
			delivery of supply. The products were initially scheduled to be delivered
			by the supplier to the subsidiary in the month of December 2016. The
			contract delivery date was scheduled for deliveries to take place
			in September 2017 as per contracts entered. Subsequently the transaction
			did not materialise and hence the subsidiary decided to buy-back
			the shares in the financial year 2017-18. Therefore, it was the
			claim that the amount of interest paid by the assessee on the investment
			made in a subsidiary -company should be allowed as a deduction as
			there was a business rational for making investment into the subsidiary
			company. It was also submitted that the sanction letter from ICICI
			Bank and Axis Bank clearly shows that<page no="752"></page>the facilities were granted
			for making overseas investment after the due diligence by those
			bankers and end-user certificates were obtained from the auditors.
			The learned Commissioner of Income-tax (Appeals) categorically noted
			that subsidiary was not carrying out any business, no documents
			in relation to the proposed plan has been furnished before the Assessing
			Officer, no business actually happened in that company and in the
			process the company incurred a loss of Rs. 171.57 crores on account
			of interest and Rs. 127.93 crores on loss on sale of shares. Except
			citing the judicial precedents, no substantive information on facts
			were produced before the Assessing Officer. The assessee failed
			to provide the financial statements of the subsidiary, fund movement
			in the books of the subsidiary, etc. In view of absence of any details
			from the side of the assessee, the learned Commissioner of Income-tax
			(Appeals) held that there is nothing brought on record to clearly
			prove that this investment was in relation to the business of the
			assessee. Accordingly, he confirmed the disallowance.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>73.</Bold> Aggrieved, the assessee is in appeal before
			us, the learned authorised representative submitted that memorandum
			of association of the assessee-company, board note relating to investment
			in the subsidiary company, audited financial statement of the subsidiary
			company are produced as additional evidence at page Nos. 629 to
			914 of the paper book. He referred to page No. 869 of the paper
			book to show that item No. 10 of the agenda was with respect to
			the new financing facility of US$ 450 million and use of proceeds
			for equity infusion into overseas subsidiaries. He submitted that the
			subsidiary is a global business licence-1 company incorporated in -Mauritius
			for the purpose of carrying out, trading related business. The joint-venture
			company will have an equity contributed by the assessee and another
			company in the ratio of 65 : 35. He further referred to page No.
			885 onwards which is the annual account of the subsidiary company
			for the year-ended on March 31, 2017. The assessee further relied
			upon the -decision of the honourable Supreme Court in the case of
			<Reference>
				<CRTo>
					<Title>S. A. Builders Ltd. v. CIT (Appeals)</Title>
				</CRTo>
			</Reference>
			<Footnote>9</Footnote> and submitted that if the
			advance to the subsidiary is for the reasons of business expediency,
			no disallowance can be made. The learned authorised representative
			further referred to page No. 287 of the paper book wherein a show-cause
			notice dated December 18, 2019 is issued with respect to the investment
			made in the subsidiary company. He further referred to page No.
			195 of the paper book wherein a letter dated December 18, 2019 was
			placed and the details of investment in subsidiary company was provided.
			He further referred to page No. 188 of the paper book wherein the
			letter dated December 16, 2019 was placed and it was<page no="753"></page>submitted that
			for the purpose of making the above investment the -company has
			obtained financial facilities from Axis Bank and ICICI Bank.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>74.</Bold> The learned Departmental representative submitted
			that no details were submitted by the assessee before the learned
			Assessing Officer. Therefore, the addition has rightly been confirmed
			by disallowing the interest expenditure. He further submitted that
			if the additional evidence were admitted, the learned Assessing
			Officer must get an opportunity to verify the same. He otherwise
			supported the orders of the learned lower authorities.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>75.</Bold> We have carefully considered the rival contention
			and perused the orders of the learned lower authorities. The brief
			facts of the case shows that assessee has made investment in a subsidiary
			company of Rs. 3,033.21 crores in Ennegaon Ltd., Mauritius consisting
			of 450 lakhs equity shares of 1 US dollar each. This fact is evident
			at note No. 16 (investments) in the annual accounts wherein two
			footnotes are also given. One of the footnotes also referred to
			another note at note No. 56 which has already been referred to by
			us in the earlier grounds. As no other details were submitted by
			the assessee except relying on certain judicial precedents and raising plea
			of commercial expediency, the disallowance was confirmed by the lower
			authorities.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>76.</Bold> Now before us the assessee has submitted
			annual accounts of the subsidiary company as well as the borrowings
			made from bankers for -making such investment. These are the additional
			evidence along with the note of the board of directors filed by
			the assessee before us which we have admitted. Therefore, if the
			additional evidence is admitted, it needs to be examined by the
			learned Assessing Officer first. In view of this we restore this
			ground of appeal back to the file of the learned Assessing Officer
			with a direction to the assessee to substantiate before the learned
			Assessing Officer that the interest expenditure incurred by the
			assessee on investment made in a subsidiary company is allowable
			as deduction. Merely -relying on the judicial precedent bereft of
			the facts of the case and unsubstantiated shelter business expediency
			without factually providing business expediency, will not help the
			case of the assessee. The learned Assessing Officer also needs to
			examine note No. 7 of accounts of subsidiary -company and whether
			the assessee has any interest in that transaction or not. The learned
			Assessing Officer may also examine the sanction letters of the banks
			on this issues, mere board notes will not suffice the facts of business
			expediency. The learned Assessing Officer may examine the details submitted
			by the assessee and after enquiry on facts, decide the issue afresh
			about the allowability of interest expenditure of Rs. 1,71,57,00,000.
			It<page no="754"></page>would be the duty of the assessee and the onus to explain before
			the learned Assessing Officer that such interest expenditure is
			deductible. The learned Assessing Officer may also grant an opportunity
			of hearing, if requested, before deciding the issue afresh. In view
			of this ground Nos. 6-7 of the appeal is allowed with above direction.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>77.</Bold> Ground No. 8 i with respect to non-granting
			of the tax deduction at source credit of Rs. 229 lakhs. Both the
			parties agreed that this is an issue of credit of tax deduction
			at source to the assessee which may be verified by the learned Assessing
			Officer. In view of this, we direct the assessee to -substantiate
			its claim of the above credit before the learned Assessing Officer
			who may decide the issue after verification on its own merits. Accordingly
			ground No. 8 of the appeal of the assessee is allowed with above
			direction.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>78.</Bold> Ground No. 9 of the appeal is with respect
			to the claim of the assessee of absence of an approach and opportunity
			of personal hearing. Before us, this ground of appeal was never
			argued and no evidence were placed before us, therefore same is
			dismissed.
		</Para>
		<Para>
			<Bold>79.</Bold> In the result appeal of the assessee is partly
			allowed for statistical purposes.
		</Para>
		<Para>Order pronounced in the open court on September 11, 2024.</Para>
	</JudgmentGroup>
	<Footnotes>
		<Link>1</Link>
		<LinkCont>
			2024
			SCC OnLine ITAT 1806.
		</LinkCont>
	</Footnotes>
	<Footnotes>
		<Link>2</Link>
		<LinkCont>
			[2007] 288 ITR 1 (SC) ; (2007) 1 SCC 781 ; 2006 SCC OnLine
			SC 1411.
		</LinkCont>
	</Footnotes>
	<Footnotes>
		<Link>3</Link>
		<LinkCont>
			[1979] 119 ITR 380
			(Bom) ; 1976 SCC OnLine Bom 197.
		</LinkCont>
	</Footnotes>
	<Footnotes>
		<Link>4</Link>
		<LinkCont>[2015] 63 taxmann.com 283 (Bom).</LinkCont>
	</Footnotes>
	<Footnotes>
		<Link>5</Link>
		<LinkCont>
			[2012] 342
			ITR 285 (Bom) ; 2012 SCC OnLine Bom 296.
		</LinkCont>
	</Footnotes>
	<Footnotes>
		<Link>6</Link>
		<LinkCont>
			[2021]
			439 ITR 399 (Bom) ; 2021 SCC OnLine Bom 14059.
		</LinkCont>
	</Footnotes>
	<Footnotes>
		<Link>7</Link>
		<LinkCont>
			[1960]
			38 ITR 413 (Mad) ; 1959 SCC OnLine Mad 229.
		</LinkCont>
	</Footnotes>
	<Footnotes>
		<Link>8</Link>
		<LinkCont>
			[1996] 220 ITR 185 (SC) ; (1996) 9 SCC 25 ; 1996
			SCC OnLine SC 140.
		</LinkCont>
	</Footnotes>
	<Footnotes>
		<Link>9</Link>
		<LinkCont>
			[2007] 288 ITR 1 (SC) ; (2007) 1 SCC 781 ; 2006
			SCC OnLine SC 1411.
		</LinkCont>
	</Footnotes>
</TCase>